<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The second part of the heroine musqueteer, or, The female warrier a true history very delightful and full of pleasant adventures in the Campagnes of 1676, &amp; 1677 / Translated out of French.</title>
            <title>Héroïne mousquetaire. Seconde partie English</title>
            <author>Préchac, Jean de, 1647?-1720.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1678</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 118 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 67 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B09764</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3208</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R182015</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">61297134</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 61297134</idno>
            <idno type="VID">180651</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B09764)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 180651)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2838:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The second part of the heroine musqueteer, or, The female warrier a true history very delightful and full of pleasant adventures in the Campagnes of 1676, &amp; 1677 / Translated out of French.</title>
                  <title>Héroïne mousquetaire. Seconde partie English</title>
                  <author>Préchac, Jean de, 1647?-1720.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 125, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J. Magnes and R. Bentley and J. Tonson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1678.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of the second part of author's L'héroine mousquetaire.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Jean de Préchac. Cf. Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages tightly bound with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Includes publisher's catalog on 2 p. at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: University of Chicago. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>English literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:180651:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE SECOND PART OF THE Heroine Muſqueteer: OR, THE FEMALE Warrier. A TRUE HISTORY: Very delightful, and full of Pleaſant Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures in the Campagnes of 1676, &amp; 1677.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated out of</hi> French.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>J. Magnes</hi> and <hi>R. Bentley,</hi> in <hi>Ruſſel-ſtreet</hi> in <hi>Covent-Garden,</hi> and <hi>J. Tonſon,</hi> at the <hi>Judges-head</hi> in <hi>Chancery-Lane,</hi> near <hi>Fleet-ſtreet.</hi> 1678.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:180651:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:180651:2"/>
            <p>Licenſed,</p>
            <p>Feb. 1. 1677/8.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>R. L'Eſtrange.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:180651:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:180651:3"/>
            <head>THE Heroin Muſqueteer: OR, The Female Warrier.</head>
            <head type="sub">PART. II.</head>
            <p>NEver was Man ſo aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht as the Marqueſs <hi>d' Oſſeyra,</hi> when he found he had wounded his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs the ſame moment, and with the ſame Weapon he thought he had taken Revenge of his Rival. The Count <hi>de Benavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dez</hi> gave him an account of all that had happen'd, when he ſurpriz'd (the ſuppos'd) S. <hi>Aubin</hi> with his Lady, and particularly of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries he fancy'd he had made of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:180651:4"/>the Intelligence between them: The Relation was ſo ſurprizing, and the Circumſtances ſo extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, the Marqueſs was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded, and under ſo ſtrong a Convulſion of different Paſſions, that what with fear, what with grief, he was Mute for ſome time, and appear'd like a Statue without Senſe or Motion: But the Paſſion he had had for <hi>Chriſtina</hi> prevailing over the reſt, and reproaching him fecretly with having deſtroy'd her, he pray'd the Count to go inſtantly learn what news of her wound; the diſorder he was in being ſo great, he had not the confidence to viſit her; but he follow'd the Count, though he ſcarce knew what he did. At the news of the Rancounter, ſeveral of his Friends flock'd to the Marqueſs; ſome of the Commanders were ſo imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently officious, they would needs ſtop him from going any further,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:180651:4"/>to ſave him the trouble of ſeeing his Enemy the ſecond time: But the return he made their miſtaken Civility, was ſo unexpectedly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toward, his beſt Friends not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the motions of his heart, were highly offended at it. They were all amaz'd to ſee him ſo troubled, and not one could imagine what reaſon he ſhould have to go to the Count of <hi>Benavidez</hi>'s, where he knew they had carried his Enemy S. <hi>Aubin.</hi> The Marqueſs was not inclin'd to violent courſes, yet they apprehended he might uſe his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to ruine the unfortunate Perſon that ſo publickly ingag'd him. A Colonel, his Friend, was ſo officious, that to prevent a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief he dreaded ſo much, he met him by the way, and intreated him to go no further, aſſuring him S. <hi>Aubin</hi> was ſo deſperately ill, he could not live an hour longer. This was the Critical moment the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:180651:5"/>really needed the aſſiſtance of his Friends, and had they not hindred him, he had certainly ſtabb'd himſelf. The Count <hi>de Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>navidez</hi> mindful of the diſorder he had left him in, return'd as haſtily as he could, to let him know S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin</hi>'s wound was not dangerous: But the Marqueſs, who began to relapſe into the extremity of his firſt Paſſion for <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> was ſo fully prepoſſeſt with the diſcourſe of the Colonel, that he thought the Count did out of kindneſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal the danger S. <hi>Aubin</hi> was in, and was loth to tell him News he knew would grieve him. This made the Marqueſs reſolve perſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to viſit S. <hi>Aubin</hi> in his Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; and he had certainly done it, had net the Count diverted him, by repreſenting the inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces might attend the ſurprize and diſcoveries their firſt Enterview would occaſion before ſo many per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:180651:5"/>who were of his Retinue, and then bore him Company. The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs yielded to the perſwaſions of his Friend, but not till the Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgion had aſſur'd him, the wound he thought ſo dangerous would be cur'd in a ſhort time. The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs could not forbear telling the Chyrurgion his Life ſhould anſwer for S. <hi>Aubin</hi>'s; and ſwore to him, that if he dy'd, he ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd to make ready to follow him preſently into another World. This being paſt, they brought the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs home, where he was viſited by all the Perſons of Quality in the Court at <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> who comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented him for his pretended ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage: Some carried on the Complement ſo far, that they blam'd him for the trouble he was in, having ſo great reaſon to be ſatisfi'd with the advantage he had gain'd over one of the braveſt men of <hi>France.</hi> He was ſo tir'd with
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:180651:6"/>theſe troubleſome Civilities, that to be rid of them, he was forc'd to give order to his Porter to ſay, he was not to be ſpoke with. The Count <hi>de Benavidez</hi> loth to leave him under ſo much vexation, ſtaid with him, in hopes by his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany to eaſe him a little of the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny of his Paſſions. As ſoon as they were alone, the Marqueſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jur'd him, to tell him truly what he thought of <hi>Chriſtina</hi>'s wound: The Count aſſur'd him it was very ſlight; and to pleaſure him, offer'd to prepare <hi>Chriſtina</hi> to receive his Viſit that night. This offer com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted the Marqueſs, and the Count had no ſooner made it, but he was forc'd to go home to find means to ſatisfie the impatience of his Friend. At his return, he found his Wife was gone to <hi>Chriſtina</hi>'s Chamber, and he took the advantage of it to give her a Viſit: When he had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt the trouble he was under for
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:180651:6"/>her misfortune, he aſſur'd her the Marqueſs was almoſt diſtracted at it, and begg'd her permiſſion to throw himſelf at her feet. <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtina</hi> thinking the Marqueſs ſtill took her for S. <hi>Aubin,</hi> not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Count had told him all, was extremely ſurpriz'd at the news; and anſwering, ſhe paſſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately deſir'd to juſtifie her ſelf, and let the Marqueſs know ſhe was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of betraying ſo generous a Friend, who had ſo highly oblig'd her. The Count haſted away to carry his Friend the good News, and ſhortly after both entred the Chamber where <hi>Chriſtina</hi> lay, who taking upon her to be S. <hi>Aubin,</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd the Marqueſs he could never have been ſatisfi'd with himſelf for being ſo unfortunate as to have diſoblig'd him, had not the Counts Relation, and the generous Viſit he was pleas'd perſonally to make him, given him reaſonable hopes he was
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:180651:7"/>ſatisfi'd of his Innocence. The kind Marqueſs, as if he had forgot <hi>Chriſtina</hi> had ever been S. <hi>Aubin,</hi> anſwer'd in terms full of tranſport and tenderneſs, praying her to change her Language, and quite rid her ſelf of that unfortunate Name of S. <hi>Aubin,</hi> that had ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happily occaſion'd his miſtake, and ingag'd him blindly to attack a Life a thouſand times dearer to him than his own. He continued the diſcourſe with ſo much Paſſion and kindneſs, that <hi>Chriſtina</hi> finding it impoſſible to keep him longer in Errour, gave free vent to her tears, perhaps for joy ſhe found him ſo conſtant: However, ſhe pretended her ſelf angry with the Count for having broken his word in diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering her to the Marqueſs. The Marqueſs then telling her how much he long'd to know what had befallen her ſince ſhe left <hi>Spain,</hi> the Counteſs having obſerv'd how much
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:180651:7"/>he was concern'd for <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> ſav'd her the trouble of the Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and gave the Marqueſs a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat Relation of all the Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures <hi>Chriſtina</hi> had acquainted her with. The loving Marqueſs, who thought all along <hi>Christina</hi> was Marri'd, but hearing no ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in all the Relation, was extreme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly impatient to know the truth of that particular. But the Count ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving bethought himſelf that longer diſcourſe might incommode the Sick Party, told his Friend of it, and prevail'd with him to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw.</p>
            <p>The Marqueſs was ſo full of the Idea of <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> that he call'd to mind the ſmalleſt circumſtances of his firſt paſſion; and not able to comprehend how ſhe had left her Husband, his Love made him wiſh heartily he might find ſhe had not been Married. He could not give over muſing of his former Amour;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:180651:8"/>at length he remembred, that the Perſon he had imploid to carry her his Letter, and told him ſhe was Marry'd, was a Sergeant in a <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> Regiment in Garriſon at <hi>Valen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciennes:</hi> He preſently diſpatch'd a Meſſenger to bring him to him in all haſte: The Sergeant being ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riv'd betimes the next morning, the Marqueſs lock'd him up with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in his Chamber, and with hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible threats charged him to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare truly why he had deceiv'd him, and what reaſon he had to tell him his Miſtreſs was Married, whereas he was newly inform'd by a <hi>French</hi> Priſoner, ſhe never had been ſo. The Man was ſo aſtoniſht at the Marqueſſes Menaces, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traid by his own Conſcience, that he ſtood for a while mute as a Fiſh: But being preſs'd to tell the truth, he fell at his feet, and confeſt he had been forced by the Marchio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs his Mother to tell him that
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:180651:8"/>Lye. The Marqueſs not deſiring to know any more, ſent back the Sergeant; and not doubting but <hi>Chriſtina</hi> had been always faithful to him, he reſolv'd to love her as long as he liv'd. A Servant he had ſent to enquire of her health, brought him word ſhe was much better: With that he went pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently to her, and entred her Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the moment they were going to bloud her: But the Chyrurgion remembring how terribly the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs had threatned him the day before, was ſo diſordered at the ſight of him, that he miſs'd the Vein twice; ſo that they were forc'd to pray the Marqueſs to withdraw, and ſent for another Chyrurgion, who had a better heart, and did the buſineſs. As great care as was taken to conceal <hi>Christina</hi>'s Sex, her Combat with the Marqueſs was become the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of the Town, and the noyſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:180651:9"/>of her Adventures had inſpir'd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all a curioſity about her: Every one ſpoke of her according to his humour: The Publick is never ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfi'd with the bare truth of things, and you may believe ſo many cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances added to the diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of the Counteſs in the ſtory of <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> that coming to her Husbands Ear, he could not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear expreſſing to her his Reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and in very harſh terms. The Counteſs having already en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain'd a ſecret jealouſie againſt <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> and perceiving her ſelf the Cully of all this Intrigue, was vext at the heart to ſee her ſelf robb'd of her Gallant, and at the ſame time in diſguſt with her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band. This made her reſolve to endeavour making ſure of the Marqueſs, being ſatisfi'd, that Guilty or Innocent, ſhe ſhould be equally odious to her Husband, having the misfortune to be alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:180651:9"/>ſuſpected by him. The deſign was ſcarce fram'd into her mind, but the Marqueſs entred her Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, intreating her, that ſince he could not with decency viſit <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtina</hi> alone any longer, ſhe would favour him with her company to <hi>Chriſtina</hi>'s Chamber. The Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs receiv'd him with more kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs than ordinary; and the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs ſenſible what advantage it might be to him to have her his Friend to do him good Offices with <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> laid hold on the occaſion, and anſwer'd her Civility ſo very obligingly, it gave her great ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction.</p>
            <p>As ſoon as <hi>Chriſtina</hi> began to be ſomewhat better, ſhe was viſited by all the Perſons of Quality in the Court at <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> Curioſity mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſeveral to ſee her, who had no other reaſon to perform that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect. Her ilneſs made her look much thinner than ordinary, but
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:180651:10"/>her Complexion had mended up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on't, her long lying a-bed having recover'd the delicate white and red of her face, which the ſervice of War had miſerably tann'd. She appear'd very charming in very plain habit; and the Gentlemen of the Court expreſt ſo much eſteem for her, that it contributed very much to her cure. It may be ſaid to the praiſe of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Gentry, that they are the greateſt Gallants of any in <hi>Europe;</hi> and in menage of Intrigues, and carrying on the ſubtilties of neat and delicate Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantry, exceed the <hi>French,</hi> who value themſelves ſo much upon it. They have the Sex in ſo great Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, that to praiſe their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes, they ſeldom ſcruple to run into profaneneſs: ſo that it will not appear ſtrange, that the miſerable condition of a Perſon beautiful as <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> confin'd to her Bed upon an occaſion ſo unuſual with thoſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:180651:10"/>of her Sex, mov'd all thoſe who vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited her, to pity her extremely.</p>
            <p>But the Count <hi>de Salazar,</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of the Cittadel at <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twerp,</hi> had ſcarcely ſeen her, but he fell deſperately in Love with her. This Gentleman was a near Kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of the Counteſs <hi>de Benavidez,</hi> which gave him the advantage of viſiting her oftner than others. His Love tormented him, yet he durſt not complain of it, either fearing it might be in vain, or finding no ſmall reluctancy in himſelf to act ſo unfaithful a part againſt the Marqueſs <hi>d' Oſſeyra</hi> his Friend. Love obſerves no mean, when fixt on extraordinary perſons; and every Viſit the Count made <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> he found his Paſſion increaſe. At laſt it became ſo violent, he could not Maſter it: He thought it high time to make his Declaration, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved twenty times to tell her how much he lov'd her, and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:180651:11"/>times fail'd of the confidence to do it. After all, he reſolv'd to make his Kinſwoman his Confident; and having acquainted her with the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemence of his Paſſion, the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs pretending her ſelf very much concern'd for him, promis'd to ſerve him; though in truth the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal motive that ingag'd her in the affair, was her particular intereſt to rob <hi>Chriſtina</hi> of the Marqueſs, and at the ſame time to revenge her ſelf of her Husband for his jealouſie. <hi>Salazar</hi> aſſur'd of the Protection of the Counteſs, viſited <hi>Chriſtina</hi> very frequently, who as courteouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived him, as introduc'd into her Acquaintance by the Marqueſs. <hi>Chriſtina</hi>'s Civility made <hi>Salazar</hi> believe the Counteſs had ſpoken to <hi>Chriſtina</hi> in his favour. Being full of this Opinion, he ſpoke to her with that liberty he durſt not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe have done. <hi>Chriſtina</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving by <hi>Salazar</hi>'s diſcourſe he
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:180651:11"/>was more concern'd for her Reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very than might be expected meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from his friendſhip for the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs, made as if ſhe underſtood not his meaning; and to prevent the occaſion of a breach with him, anſwer'd in Railery his obliging expreſſions. <hi>Salazar</hi> applauded him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for the good ſucceſs of his firſt attempt: this confirm'd his Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and made him forget the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects he ſhould have retain'd for his Friend. The Counteſs <hi>de Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>navidez</hi> omitted nothing the while to rekindle the Marqueſſes flame: But finding her endeavours vain to recover for her ſelf the affection of a heart which had newly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted it ſelf to the violence of its firſt impreſſions, which are ever the ſtrongeſt, ſhe bethought her ſelf of an expedient, which (ſhe doubted not) would make her Miſtreſs of her deſign; and the better to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> pretending her
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:180651:12"/>ſelf very much her friend, ſhe told her, by way of confidence, ſhe had newly learn'd a ſecret <hi>Chriſtina</hi> was very much concern'd to know. When ſhe had made all the Pream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles uſual to ſmooth the way for a piece of ill news, ſhe fell to aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vating the unhappineſs of Women that truſt the Oaths of men who make Love to them, when after her ſignal fidelity to the Marqueſs <hi>d' Oſſeyra,</hi> he was ſtill in doubt of her, and ſet on his Friend <hi>Salazar</hi> to try her, by pretending to love her: that the Conduct of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs in this particular appear'd ſo criminal, when he had ſo great rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to reſt aſſur'd of her fidelity, that ſhe thought it her duty to make her acquainted with it as ſoon as her Kinſman <hi>Salazar</hi> had told her of it. <hi>Chriſtina</hi> calling to mind <hi>Salazar</hi>'s diſcourſe, thought the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence the Counteſs had given her of very great importance, and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:180651:12"/>no leſs ſincerity; and having ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt no ſmall reſentment againſt the Marqueſs, ſhe thank'd the Counteſs, and aſſur'd her ſhe would take her advantages of the advice ſhe had given her, and would make that fickle-headed Lover know the intereſt he had in her was not ſo well-grounded, but a proceeding ſo unhandſom and diſobliging as this might utterly deſtroy it. The Counteſs joyful to ſee her Intrigue take ſo well, and making no doubt but <hi>Chriſtina</hi> to be reveng'd of the Marqueſs would uſe <hi>Salazar</hi> well, made him ſenſible what good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice ſhe had done him, and told him he might declare himſelf freely, and never fear the ſucceſs. This made him wait on <hi>Chriſtina</hi> the oftner, and take his opportunity to make a formal Declaration of his Paſſion. <hi>Chriſtina</hi> received his Complement ſo gently and quietly, that <hi>Salazar</hi> flatter'd himſelf ſhe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:180651:13"/>was in Love with him. The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs obſerving how conſtant and diligent his Friend <hi>Salazar</hi> was in viſiting his Miſtreſs, began to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend he might be his Rival: And ſhe us'd him with that kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the Marqueſſes preſence, it almoſt diſtracted him. He made his complaints of it to <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> but ſhe made ſo light of all he ſaid, it vext him at the heart. The Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs watching all opportunities, took her advantage of theſe favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable circumſtances, to invite the Marqueſs more than ever: But all to no purpoſe; this threw her into abſolute deſpair, and made her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to ſatisfie her Revenge if ſhe could not her Love. A Woman in that condition will ſacrifice any thing to her reſentment; and the Counteſs had recourſe to new Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifices to provoke <hi>Chriſtina</hi> againſt the Marqueſs, and him againſt <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lazar:</hi> They were all ſo diſpos'd
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:180651:13"/>for her purpoſe, ſhe eaſily accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſht her deſign. The Marqueſs and <hi>Salazar</hi> were at very high words; and the Governour of the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands</hi> being inform'd of it, ordered them both to be ſecur'd. <hi>Chriſtina</hi> having newly recover'd her health, was ſo troubled ſhe had been the cauſe of ſo much noyſe, ſhe reſolv'd to return into <hi>France,</hi> and ſpend her life in a Covent, and be no longer the May-game of Love, and of Fortune. She im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted her reſolution to the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs, who ſeeming to diſapprove it, offer'd ſome weak reaſons to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert her from the deſign, though in truth ſhe was glad at heart ſhe had taken that reſolution, in hopes to ſee ſo dangerous a Rival at further diſtance, which <hi>Chriſtina</hi> might have eaſily perceived, had ſhe not been prepoſſeſt to Blindneſs with the Opinion of ſincere kindneſs ſhe thought the Counteſs had for her.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:180651:14"/>
            <p>The Dutcheſs of <hi>Arſchott</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving about that time obtain'd a Paſs-port from his Majeſty of <hi>France</hi> to go from <hi>Mons</hi> to <hi>Lille,</hi> to ſettle ſome private affairs, paſs'd through <hi>Bruſſels. Chriſtina</hi> being in ſearch of means to execute her deſign, and looking upon this as a favourable occaſion for her return into <hi>France</hi> under the Paſs-port of the Dutcheſs, communicated her thoughts to the Counteſs, who ſeeing her reſolved, facilitated all things for her private retirement, that the Marqueſs might know no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of it. She preſented her to the Dutcheſs, and ſaid in her fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour whatever ſhe thought neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to perſwade the Dutcheſs to take her along. The Dutcheſs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived her very obligingly, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd her ſelf very glad of the company of ſo lovely a Perſon. <hi>Chriſtina</hi> left <hi>Bruſſels</hi> abundantly ſatisfi'd, at leaſt in appearance, to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:180651:14"/>have the opportunity of returning to her Country, yet not without a ſecret reluctance to be at ſo great a diſtance from the Marqueſs, for whom ſhe had more kindneſs than ſhe was aware of. The Amorous Marqueſs fail'd not a day to ſend to the Counteſs to inquire of his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs: The Counteſs fearing he might have news of her departure timely enough to ſtay her, took care to tell thoſe who were going from the Marqueſs to her Lodging, that ſhe went to Bed very late the Night before, and deſired not to be awaked. The ſecond day the Counteſs laid her ſelf in the Bed <hi>Chriſtina</hi> uſually lay in, and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeiting her voice, anſwer'd the Perſon the Marqueſs had ſent to inquire of her health, that ſhe was much obliged to his Maſter for his care of her. The Counteſs had longer continued the Cheat, had not one of her Maids (who knew
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:180651:15"/>by experience the Marqueſs never fail'd to reward very liberally the ſmalleſt ſervices done him) given him intelligence of paſſages; thoſe who have been in Love can eaſily imagine the effect this News had upon the Marqueſs: He would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently have followed her, but that he continued under Confinement: the thoughts of the ill condition he was in, inſpir'd into him a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand extravagant reſolutions, when he called to mind how he had loſt a perſon he had ſo dearly lov'd in the Flower of his Youth, and had luckily met with after ſo long ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration by extraordinary Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and had no ſooner diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd her, but he yielded himſelf abſolutely at her diſpoſe. He ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly examin'd his Conduct in the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair, to the very ſmalleſt circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, but could not find any cauſe to charge himſelf with ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving occaſion'd ſo ſudden a depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture:
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:180651:15"/>it was not in his power to gueſs the reaſon of it, though ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently aſſur'd he was not the cauſe of it; but he look'd upon her remove as fatal to him, who could not live ſeparated from her. Having tir'd himſelf with reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, he thought he ſhould but la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in vain to retrieve her, who in all appearance was got already to <hi>Lille:</hi> Yet unwilling his paſſion ſhould juſtly reproach him to have omitted any thing in his power for recovering <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> he reſolv'd at all adventures, to pray the Duke <hi>de Montalto,</hi> General of the Horſe, and his very good Friend, to ſend out a ſtrong Party toward the way of <hi>Lille,</hi> with ſtrict Order to ſtay all they met with, whether with Paſs-port, or without. The Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders were punctually executed, and the Party brought in ſeveral who travelled with Paſs-ports, but no news of <hi>Chriſtina;</hi> and all this ado
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:180651:16"/>ſerv'd only to make a great deal of diſorder, and give occaſion to the Rumor rais'd about that time, that the Duke <hi>de Villa Hermoſa</hi> had call'd in all his Paſs-ports.</p>
            <p>The Marqueſs would not be diſcourag'd for all this, but ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the means to have a Letter convey'd to her, he found a man who promis'd to follow her to her very home, rather than fail to bring him an account of her. The Marqueſs in the condition he was in thought this ſome comfort; and having loaded the man with his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berality, and filled him with hopes of more, he diſpatch'd him away with this Letter:</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>WAs it in your Power to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to be gone, and leave behind you the moſt paſſionate of Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers? Did you not think me ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently mortifi'd by your permitting</hi> Salazar <hi>to preſume to make Love to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:180651:16"/>you, but you muſt utterly deſtroy me by your unkind departure? Ah Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el! Can you doubt that if you conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue your Voyage, I will not quit my Charge, my Fortune, and (it may be) my Duty to follow you? I had done it already, but that I look'd on my Imployments as advantages that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to you, and I ought to preſerve, to take away from you all pretence for reproaching my Love. Heaven is my Witneſs, that to ingage my ſelf to you with Bands indiſſoluble, I waited only the recovery of your health, with that extremity of impatience you might eaſily have perceiv'd, had you not been the moſt inſenſible per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the World. Let me know what ſhall become of me, and aſſure your ſelf, your Anſwer ſhall regulate the Deſtiny of the moſt faithful of Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>The Marqueſs</hi> d'Oſſeyra.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:180651:17"/>
            <p>When the kind Marqueſs had written this Letter, he read it ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral times, and finding it very a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to his ſentiments, thought it long till 'twas delivered to his Miſtreſs: But fearing the Bearer might by the way be taken by ſome Party, he reſolved to ſend a ſecond with ſuch another Letter, in hopes that if one miſcarried, the other might paſs ſafe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Salazar</hi> was much troubled for <hi>Chriſtina</hi>'s departure, though the deſpair his Rival was in gave him ſome comfort: The paſſionate love he had for her, and the opinion he flatter'd himſelf with, that ſhe ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him not, made him ſend after her a truſty perſon, that upon his report he might the better take his meaſures for his future Conduct: And not long after the Marqueſſes Friends, and his, reconcil'd the two Rivals, and <hi>Salazar</hi> received Order to repair to his Government.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:180651:17"/>
            <p>The Counteſs the while tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph'd for the good ſucceſs of her Artifices; and the paſſion her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of revenge had given birth to, was grown up to that violence by the reſiſtance it found from the Marqueſs, and the advantages ſhe promis'd her ſelf by the remove of her Rival, it was not in her power to conceal her joy and her tranſport from the paſſionate Lover; who far from anſwering her hopes, loaded her with reproaches; let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting her know, he was not ignorant what Tricks ſhe had us'd to make his Miſtreſs fall out with him. This touch'd her to the quick, and put her into ſuch a confuſion, and ſo deſperate a fret, to ſee her Artifices diſcovered, ſhe took her Bed upon't that very day, and continued a long time very dangerouſly ill; the Phyſitians who attended her ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving never diſcover'd the cauſe of her diſtemper, but uſing Remedies
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:180651:18"/>for Diſeaſes ſhe never was troubled with.</p>
            <p>While the Counteſs was in Cure, the Dutcheſs of <hi>Arſchott</hi> was at <hi>Lille,</hi> ſo well-pleas'd with the agreeable Converſation of <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> that ſhe intreated her company, at leaſt for the time ſhe tarried at <hi>Lille. Chriſtina</hi> finding her ſelf ſtaid by reaſons ſhe could not maſter, eaſily conſented, being glad of a pretence to continue a little longer in <hi>Flanders.</hi> He whom <hi>Salazar</hi> had imploid to inquire af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter her, had learnt ſhe was to ſpend ſome days at the Dutcheſs of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſchott</hi>'s; and as he returned to give <hi>Salazar</hi> that account, he met one of the Marqueſſes Meſſengers; and being a witty man, and well-acquainted with <hi>Salazar</hi>'s ſecrets, he preſently ſuſpected the Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers buſineſs, and examin'd him ſo cunningly, that at laſt he diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd the occaſion of his Journey:
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:180651:18"/>And applying himſelf after to get out of his hands the Marqueſſes Letter, he ſet about him ſo dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouſly, that he finger'd the Letter, and carried it to <hi>Salazar,</hi> who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it with all the ſatisfaction i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginable. But the Marqueſſes o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Meſſenger more fortunate than his Fellow, delivered his Letter to <hi>Chriſtina;</hi> who heartily glad of it, was extremely ſatisfied to find the expreſſions ſo paſſionately kind, and anſwer'd it thus:</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THank your own Jealouſie, and reproach not me ſo unjuſtly, that I admitted of</hi> Salazar<hi>'s Addreſſes: The paſſion of Love is none of the weakneſſes I am ſubject to; yet I muſt own, I make a great difference between you, and any other man; and find, that could you be conſtant to the ſentiments expreſt in your Letter, it will be very difficult for me to hold the reſolution I have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:180651:19"/>never to love. The Dutcheſs of</hi> Arſchott <hi>hath a deſire to keep me here, and I cannot deny her, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out appearing unworthy of the kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſhe hath for me. In the mean time you may aſſure your ſelf, no perſon hath a greater reſpect for you than</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Chriſtina.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The Marqueſs having received this Letter two days after it was writ, was ſo well-pleas'd with it that he never inquir'd whether both his Letters were delivered. He kiſs'd <hi>Chriſtina</hi>'s a thouſand times over; and impatiently long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſee her, he did nothing but think of the means how to do it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The enterprize was dangerous, and he ſaw well enough what a hazard he ſhould run to enter an Enemies Town, where the vigilance of the Governour juſtly heightned his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of being ſurprized.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:180651:19"/>
            <p>But Love, which never loves long debates, eſpecially ſuch as tend to keep it at diſtance from its object, quickly ſuggeſted an expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient the Marqueſs thought infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. He procur'd from the Marſhal <hi>d' Humiers</hi> a Paſs-port for a Pedler of <hi>Bruſſels</hi> to go trade at <hi>Lille;</hi> and having got ſome <hi>Engliſh Point,</hi> the beſt he could meet with, he went for <hi>Lille,</hi> and eaſily got en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance to the Dutcheſs of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſchott</hi>'s, under pretence to ſell his Points; which were ſo fine, and ſo very cheap, he ſold many of them to the Dutcheſs, and her Women. At laſt he was brought into <hi>Chriſtina</hi>'s apartment, who ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry luckily was alone in her Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, perhaps to read over the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſes Letter.</p>
            <p>The Love ſhe had for him pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd the Idea of him ſo freſh in her mind, that diſguiz'd as he was, ſhe knew him at firſt ſight; and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:180651:20"/>concealing her ſurprize, ſhe pray'd the Dutcheſſes Maid who had brought in the Pedler, to go call another Maid who had good skill in Points. By good fortune that Maid was abroad, and ſhe who had been to call her being withdrawn, the two Lovers having clear'd all miſunderſtandings, and the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs having juſtifi'd himſelf, they had the opportunity to expreſs themſelves with all the freedom and tenderneſs imaginable. <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtina</hi> quarrell'd with him for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving expos'd himſelf to ſuch evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent danger: the Marqueſs took that occaſion to tell her, that if ſhe were ſo much concern'd for his danger, as ſhe appear'd, ſhe might eaſily prevent his expoſing himſelf for the future, by permitting him to take her back with him to <hi>Bruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels,</hi> and marry her. She confeſt with ſome trouble, ſhe could find in her heart to do it; yet found by
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:180651:20"/>her ſelf, it would be impoſſible for her to reſolve to be married to an Enemy of the Kings: What, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupts the Marqueſs, would you have me then be a Traytor to my Prince, and my Country? I am not ſo unjuſt, replies <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> nor can I think you capable of ſuch a thought, and ſhould eſteem you much leſs if you were: But there is hope the War will not laſt ever; and the ſcruples you make to be marry'd to an Enemy of your Prince, I may very juſtly pretend to, would my love give me leave: Do not you think we ſufficiently eſpouſe the Quarrel of our Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigns, by ſacrificing every day our Lives and our Fortunes to their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, without making our Love a part of the Sacrifice? But pray, let's have no more of theſe matters of State, but imploy better the moments of a Converſation hath coſt me ſo dear<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Company coming
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:180651:21"/>in as he was ſpeaking, <hi>Chriſtina</hi> was forced to diſmiſs the pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Pedler, and appoint him to come two hours after to her, being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to buy any thing till ſhe had firſt ſhewn it to one who had judgment in it. He went away diſpleas'd he was ſo unhappily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted. <hi>Chriſtina</hi> ſeeing it would be hard for her to have private diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe with him, writ him a Billet which ſhe reſolv'd to deliver him ſecretly, to let him know her mind.</p>
            <p>The ſuppos'd Pedler being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd at the hour aſſign'd, <hi>Chriſtina</hi> who was in the Dutcheſſes Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber went to meet him at the door, and told him aloud, ſhe had as much <hi>Engliſh Point</hi> as ſhe needed, and would buy none but <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> which pleas'd her beſt of any. With that ſhe neatly ſlipped into the Marqueſſes hand a Billet to this effect:</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:180651:21"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>I <hi>Cannot without fear ſee you here: if you love me, provide for your ſafety, and stay not a moment in a place ſo dangerous for you as this. Time peradventure will be more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable to us than we can hope for at preſent. The Dutcheſs is ſo obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, I doubt not but ſhe will ingage me to continue here longer: if I comply with her, you may believe 'tis much for your ſake. Once more, let me beg you inſtantly be gone, and think that my repoſe depends on your ſafety.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The Marqueſs having under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by this Billet the diſquiet of his Miſtreſs, return'd for <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> and appear'd at Court before they miſs'd him: the Dutcheſs of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſchott</hi> was the mean time viſited by all the Perſons of Quality at <hi>Lille,</hi> her Merit no leſs than the reſpect due to her Birth, drawing
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:180651:22"/>to her Houſe all the good company of the Town. The Marchioneſs <hi>de Belabre,</hi> in her return from <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> (where ſhe had been caſt in her Suit) gave the Dutcheſs a Viſit, and was extremely ſurpriz'd at the ſight of <hi>Chriſtina</hi> there, whom ſhe preſently knew for S. <hi>Aubin;</hi> and calling to mind the laſt years Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naval, ſhe made no doubt but Love had a great ſhare in this new diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guize; and according to moſt Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens humour, thinking it a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty matter to penetrate the depth of an Amorous Intrigue, ſhe was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to applaud her ſelf for the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery ſhe had made; and to carry on her deſign, came frequently to the Dutcheſſes. <hi>Chriſtina</hi> having been very well acquainted with the Marchioneſs at <hi>Paris,</hi> preſently knew her; and not able to forbear bluſhing as often as ſhe ſaw her, ſhe reſolv'd to take her time to ſpeak to her in private, and unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:180651:22"/>her: But the Marchioneſs out of exceſs of diſcretion always a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided her; and perceiving it trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> ſhe came to her one day, and whiſper'd her in the Ear, <hi>Trouble not your ſelf, and never fear me, I can keep my Friends counſel. Chriſtina</hi> endeavour'd to diſabuſe her, but in vain. The Marchioneſs having a ſtrong fancy ſhe knew the Lady had ingag'd S. <hi>Aubin</hi> to put on this diſguize, though ſhe made a thouſand falſe gueſſes: for as ſoon as ſhe ſaw S. <hi>Aubin</hi> ſpeak to any Lady, imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately ſhe concluded ſhe was the Perſon.</p>
            <p>After much labour in vain, and fruitleſs obſervation, the Marchio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs made the Baroneſs of S. <hi>Sau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veur</hi> her Confident in the buſineſs, imparting to her the Mighty My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery; imagining S. <hi>Aubin</hi> not mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſting the Baroneſs, ſhe would not be ſo reſerv'd in her preſence;
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:180651:23"/>and ſo ſhe might eaſily find out the truth of what ſhe earneſtly deſir'd to know. The Baroneſs being a young Lady, and of a very jovial humour, was raviſh'd with joy at the diſcovery of ſuch a Secret, and applying her ſelf to a buſineſs ſo ſuitable to her humour, ſhe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd <hi>Chriſtina</hi> with a great deal of care, though little ſatisfaction. Angred at her ill ſucceſs, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending the Marchioneſs would impute it to her want of Addreſs, ſhe doubled her diligence, and watch'd <hi>Chriſtina</hi> more narrowly than before: But all this care and extremity of attention ſerv'd for no more, than to make her take better notice of the good meen of the pretended Gentleman. She thought him ſo amiable, and took ſuch delight in viewing him, that in a ſhort time ſhe found her Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity had produc'd an effect quite other than ſhe expected, having
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:180651:23"/>inſenſibly ingag'd her in a paſſion for S. <hi>Aubin</hi> which was already ſo ſtrong, ſhe perceiv'd ſhe was not Miſtreſs of it. This made her long for an intimate acquaintance with ſo Charming a Perſon; and the better to obtain it, ſhe ſought for occaſions of ſeeing and diſcourſing her; which was eaſie to find, all Perſons of Quality having free ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs to the Dutcheſſes. <hi>Chriſtina</hi> ſatisfi'd the longing of the Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs with ſo good a Grace, ſhe was no leſs pleas'd with her Civility, than taken with her good meen. She was a hundred times upon the point of telling her, ſhe knew the ſecret of her Sex; and that natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral modeſty that ſticks ſo cloſe to Women well-born, made her as often change her reſolution, and quit her deſign. After many Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts in her heart, where Love, Modeſty, Freedom and Reſerved<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſtrove in vain to get the better
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:180651:24"/>one over the other, ſhe found <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtina</hi> alone, and adventur'd to tell her, ſhe had never known a Perſon ſo deſerving of Love as ſhe was, and that had Heaven made her of a Sex different from hers, ſhe ſhould have found it very difficult to ſave her ſelf from paſſion for a perſon ſo amiable. <hi>Chriſtina</hi> who thought of nothing leſs than Love, thought this diſcourſe an effect of her friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; and anſwer'd, ſhe was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely oblig'd to her for her kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, aſſuring her ſhe would endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to return it her with all the tenderneſs of affection ſhe was ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of. The Baroneſs having al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready advanc'd ſo far, was not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfi'd with ſo cold an anſwer: However, ſhe thought it neceſſary to appear content for the preſent, and to prevent the loſs of all, ſhe imbrac'd her tenderly, and gave her many thanks. The Dutcheſs coming in, and finding them in that
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:180651:24"/>poſture, ask'd the reaſon. The Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneſs who thought her imbraces as criminal as <hi>Chriſtina</hi> believ'd them innocent, anſwer'd with ſome trouble (for a pretence to deceive the Dutcheſs) that ſhe was upon going, and could not take leave without imbracing her dear friend. What ſhe ſaid was believ'd, not one having perceived how heartily ſhe was vext to leave a Houſe where ſhe ſo much lov'd to be.</p>
            <p>Every time the Marchioneſs ſaw the Baroneſs <hi>de</hi> S. <hi>Sauveur,</hi> ſhe ask'd if ſhe had not found out the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons why S. <hi>Aubin</hi> had diſguiz'd himſelf: But having no account to ſatisfie her Curioſity, ſhe became more impatient, and reſolv'd to know it one way or other. Having mus'd a while, ſhe reſolv'd to tell her (whom ſhe thought S. <hi>Aubin</hi>) of the buſineſs, and to oblige him to impart to her the ſecret of his Love; and in caſe of refuſal, to
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:180651:25"/>threaten him ſhe would publiſh the ſecret of his Sex. <hi>Chriſtina</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely ſurpriz'd with the Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal, would have undeceiv'd her, by making her a ſaithful Relation of her Adventures. But the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs prepoſſeſt with an Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhe ſpoke to S. <hi>Aubin,</hi> gave no credit to the diſcourſe, telling him, ſhe would allow him till that time to morrow to think on't, aſſuring him he might relye on her diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but if he delay'd any longer to acquaint her with the ſecret, ſhe would certainly ſpoil all. <hi>Chriſtina</hi> who conceal'd nothing from the Dutcheſs, gave her an account of the perplexity ſhe was in, by the earneſt ſolicitations of the Marchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oneſs. This was good ſport for them, and made them laugh hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily, and reſolve together, ſince the Marchioneſs was ſo abſolutely bent to be deceiv'd, and not be diſabus'd, they would for their divertiſement
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:180651:25"/>afford their help to deceive her: the ſole queſtion remain'd was, what Lady ſhould be the Object of the pretended paſſion: Several were in nomination, but none ſo likely to take as the Baroneſs <hi>de</hi> S. <hi>Sau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veur,</hi> being a handſom and jovial young Lady, and <hi>Chriſtina</hi>'s inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate friend. The Marchioneſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing told of it, was ſurpriz'd at the news, but promis'd to keep his counſel, and expreſt great ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction at the confidence he repos'd in her.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> by agreement with the Dutcheſs affected thenceforward ſo much kindneſs and care for the Baroneſs <hi>de</hi> S. <hi>Sauveur,</hi> and to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear ſo much concern'd for her, and ſtill long for her company, which the Baroneſs anſwer'd on her part with a great deal of pleaſure, that the Marchioneſs having often obſerv'd them, was confirm'd in her Errour; and inwardly applauding
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:180651:26"/>her ſelf for having ſo luckily diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd the Intrigue, would needs make the Baroneſs ſenſible of it, that ſhe might know her ſelf at her mercy for the diſcovery. And not longer able to keep a ſecret which was already a burden to her, ſhe gave her a viſit; and having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach'd her for not dealing clearly by her, in concealing her know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of S. <hi>Aubin</hi>'s paſſion; In ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, ſays ſhe, by way of Railery, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> was not ill prepar'd to penetrate S. <hi>Aubin</hi>'s concerns, and you have acted your part very well, only 'tis pity you had not to do with a Fool. All things ſeem'd to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire to deceive the Marchioneſs; for the Baroneſs bluſhing, made her think that change of her counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance an effect of her confuſion at the diſcovery ſhe had made. You do not deſerve, adds the Marchio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, I ſhould uſe ſo much diſcretion in your concern, who were ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:180651:26"/>to make me of your coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el: But fear me not, had I not promis'd S. <hi>Aubin</hi> ſecreſie at his confeſſion, the reſpect I have for you would oblige me to ſilence. The Baroneſs ſurpriz'd at the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, ſtood mute for ſome time, not knowing what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> think on't: but as we eaſily believe what we paſſionately deſire, the Baroneſs no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nger doubting but S. <hi>Aubin</hi> lov'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er, and that the Marchioneſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oke in good earneſt, quickly paſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut of a great aſtoniſhment into a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r greater joy: If a man will love one, ſays ſhe, how can we help it? Would you not think it hard to throw a Gentleman into deſpair, who does things ſo extraordinary for his Miſtreſs, and demonſtrates by his actions the violence of his paſſion? I will pardon you, replies the Marchioneſs, your want of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in me hitherto, upon condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion you will hide nothing from me
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:180651:27"/>for the future. It was agreed, and they parted both very well-pleas'd with their miſtakes; the Marchio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to ſee her ſelf the Confident in an Intrigue ſhe had ſo great a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to penetrate; the Baroneſs to be aſſured by ſo good a hand thing that did ſo much flatter her paſſion She was ſo fully perſwaded S. <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin</hi> was in love with her, ſhe bega<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to repent ſhe had been ſo forward to let him know the kindneſs ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> had for him, fearing it might have leſſen'd the eſteem ſhe could will he ſhould have for her. This made her reſolve to force her ſelf into more reſervedneſs, and be more ſhy for a while, to ſet an edge o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his paſſion. It fell out as ſhe wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; for <hi>Chriſtina</hi> to mainta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> throughout the part ſhe was to a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> for the Dutcheſſes divertiſement and her own, was every day kinde than other to the Baroneſs, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> through diſſimulation (uſual with
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:180651:27"/>Women) receiving <hi>Chriſtina</hi>'s Courtſhip very coldly, hop'd by that means to heighten the paſſion of her ſuppoſed Lover.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſtina</hi> not knowing the inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Baroneſs, nor the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſhe us'd her ſo, took ſo ill the ſlight return ſhe made of her Civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, that ſhe forbore the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of them, and ſhunn'd her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, to prevent occaſions of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe with her. The Baroneſs perceiving it, could not brook this indifference above a day; the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row ſhe goes to <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> and in ſome heat ask'd her what ſhe had done to be ſlighted ſo by her, and make her affect avoiding her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, as ſhe obſerv'd ſhe did. She let fall ſome other haſty words, which ſurpriz'd <hi>Chriſtina</hi> extreme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; who anſwer'd, ſhe had never been wanting to the friendſhip ſhe had promis'd her; but that the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneſs had appear'd ſo cold the day
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:180651:28"/>before towards her, ſhe had no reaſon to wonder it had made her more ſhy. The Baroneſs was ſo impatient, ſhe would not allow he time to finiſh, but imbrac'd her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly, and was upon the point of telling her, 'twas in vain to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour concealing his Sex from her, who knew it already, by very good information: But ſhe forbore foreſeeing ſhe could not with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency take ſome little libertie with S. <hi>Aubin</hi> diſcover'd ſhe us'd with <hi>Chriſtina</hi> diſguiz'd. Never did Woman love more to deceive her ſelf, and never was there love of ſo ſingular a Character. Preſs'd by her paſſion, ſhe gave S. <hi>Aubin</hi> thouſand occaſions to declare him ſelf to be what ſhe took him for but finding all would not do, and attributing it to his fear, ſhe ſtudie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a thouſand expedients to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh an Adventure ſhe could not endure ſhould hang in ſuſpence.
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:180651:28"/>Time furniſh'd her with an unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected occaſion: Her Husband be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing gone one Evening for the Country, ſhe ſat up very late at the Dutcheſſes, and having cunningly let fall a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>word, ſhe would willingly lye there that night: She ask'd one of the Dutcheſſes Women if ſhe would admit her her Bedfellow: <hi>Chriſtina</hi> offer'd her a part of her Bed; the Baroneſs at firſt ſeem'd loth to accept of it, for fear of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commoding her, but at laſt ſhe was perſwaded, the Maid ſhe had firſt ſpoken to having a Bedfellow already, which the Baroneſs knew, though ſhe pretended the contrary.</p>
            <p>When they were juſt ready to go to bed, the Baroneſs retaining ſome remains of modeſty, was ſo troubled, and out of countenance, ſhe knew not what ſhe did. But to give her dying Vertue ſome ſmall ſatisfaction for the diſorder her paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion had brought her in, ſhe told
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:180651:29"/>
               <hi>Chriſtina</hi> ſhe would have only one corner of the bed, where ſhe pray'd her to let her ſleep quietly without touching her all night. <hi>Chriſtin</hi> very readily promis'd what ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſir'd, and as readily perform'd i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> When the Lights were taken a way, the Baroneſs who expected with impatience the darkneſs ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap> long'd for, was aſtoniſht to fin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Chriſtina</hi> faſt aſleep. At firſt ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap> thought it her own fault, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> her Gallant feign'd himſelf aſle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to expreſs his obedience to he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> yet ſhe knew not what to thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> on't. But having long expected vain to find him more confider ſhe ask'd him if he were aſlee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> but receiving no anſwer, it alm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> put her beſide her ſelf. She fell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſighing, but her ſighs as little <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> fected <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> who was in a de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſleep. The Baroneſs thought tw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty times to awake her, but ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and vexation made her forbe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:180651:29"/>Never had Woman ſo bad a night, though never Woman expected a better. At length it was day; and ſeeing her inſenſible Lover lye ſtill as a Stock, ſhe dreſs'd her ſelf ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtily; and the deſpair ſhe was in not permitting her to quit the Room without leaving behind her ſome mark of her reſentment, ſhe found Pen, Ink and Paper ready on the Table, and writ immediately this Billet:</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>I <hi>Have receiv'd from you the moſt ſenſible outrage a Lady can ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer; but 'tis what I deſerv'd, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſo blindly abandon'd my ſelf to a paſſion for a man who knew no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to anſwer it. I muſt now endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to cover my ſhame: As for you, I adviſe you to continue the diſguize that becomes you ſo well. You have already the modeſty of the Sex whoſe habit you carry; and you are not to deſpair, but Heaven ſenſible of its
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:180651:30"/>Errour in making you a Man, me take from you that little you have r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> maining of that Sex.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The Baroneſs having written the Letter, laid it on <hi>Chriſtina</hi>'s To<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> lette, and withdrew. As ſoon a ſhe got home, ſhe feign'd ſhe ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> been all night up at Play; and h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ving had her ſelf undreſt, went pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently to bed, which you may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve was not very eaſie to her <hi>Chriſtina</hi> at getting up having found the Billet, dreſt her ſelf in a haſte to carry it to the Dutcheſs: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> made them good ſport; and when they reflected on the courſe the Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> roneſs had taken to get an intereſt in <hi>Christina,</hi> they concluded the Marchioneſs had imparted her ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret to her, and ſo involv'd her in the ſame Errour with her ſelf.</p>
            <p>The Dutcheſs was concern'd at it, and had the goodneſs to go to the Baroneſs to undeceive her; and
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:180651:30"/>having fully told her what ſhe knew of the buſineſs, at laſt, though with difficulty, diſabus'd her. She would have gone thence to the Marchioneſs of <hi>Belabre</hi> to do her the like good office: but the Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſufficiently confounded alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and fearing further explication might reflect more on her Credit, intreated the Dutcheſs to ſay no more of it, but to leave the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs to her miſtakes, as not da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to truſt her diſcretion in ſo tender a point, where the matter appear'd ſo fit for mirth, and her Reputation was ſo deeply con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd.</p>
            <p>The Dutcheſs had now almoſt finiſh'd her buſineſs at <hi>Lille,</hi> and had written to <hi>Bruſſels</hi> ſhe would return thither ſpeedily, and hop'd to bring <hi>Chriſtina</hi> back again with her. The Counteſs <hi>de Benavidez,</hi> who was pretty well recover'd, and had not loſt by her ſickneſs any
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:180651:31"/>part of her paſſion for the Marque <hi>d' Oſſeyra,</hi> hearing talk of <hi>Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtina</hi>'s return, was ſo frighted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the News, ſhe made it her buſine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by all means to prevent it; and length found an occaſion to have Letter writ to the Dutcheſs of <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſchott</hi> by a Lady, and of her be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Friends, to inform her ſhe was wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> impatience expected at <hi>Bruſſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> that her concerns being very de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to her, ſhe thought fit to acquai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> her there was great murmuring Court that ſhe had thoughts bringing back <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> who wou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> not fail to give intelligence to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>French</hi> of all ſhe could learn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Bruſſels;</hi> at leaſt it would be b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> liev'd ſo, <hi>Chriſtina</hi> being alrea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> under ſuſpition of Guilt in that pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular. The Dutcheſs being hig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concern'd to hold fair with th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and fearing their j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie of her long ſtay at <hi>Lille,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſpecially ſince the News ſpread <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:180651:31"/>
               <hi>Flanders</hi> of her having had a hand in the Marriage of the Prince of <hi>Izinguien</hi> with the Daughter of the Marſhal <hi>d' Humiers,</hi> look'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the advice as not to be ſlighted: And whatever kindneſs ſhe had for <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> ſhe could not find in her heart to expoſe her ſelf to ruine for her ſake, in praying her to bear her company to <hi>Bruſſels.</hi> As they were alone one day, the Dutcheſs took her opportunity to make a long diſcourſe of the ſtate of her affairs, and the neceſſity ſhe was under to avoid any thing that might give a jealouſie of her to the <hi>Spaniards:</hi> adding, that this oblig'd her to be very cautious in her Conduct, and to deny her ſelf many things in themſelves very agreeable to her. <hi>Chriſtina</hi> had too much Wit not to apprehend the meaning of this diſcourſe, and anſwer'd, ſhe had for the ſame reaſons reſolv'd to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn into <hi>France,</hi> as ſoon as ſhe
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:180651:32"/>ſhould receive Anſwer to a Letter ſhe had writ into her Country; and in the mean time to put her ſelf into a Covent. They concluded their diſcourſe with mutual aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances of Eternal Friendſhip; and two days before the Dutcheſs left <hi>Lille, Chriſtina</hi> entred the Covent of the Nuns of S. <hi>Thomas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Marqueſs <hi>d' Oſſeyra</hi> ſeeing the Dutcheſs arriv'd at <hi>Bruſſels</hi> without <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> was very much alarm'd at it, and went in great haſte to inquire the news of her. When he heard ſhe was gone into a Nunnery, it extremely diſturb'd him, not knowing what reaſon ſhe had for it: But the Counteſs <hi>de Benavidez</hi> watching all occaſions to vex him, dextrouſly gave out, that <hi>Chriſtina</hi> had long ſince pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately communicated to her the diſguſt ſhe had for the World, and the deſign ſhe had eſpous'd to ſpend her days in a Religious Houſe. This
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:180651:32"/>coming to the Marqueſſes ear, the violence of his affection allow'd him ſo little time of conſideration, that he went away that Evening for <hi>Lille,</hi> with his former Paſs-port as a Pedler; and made ſuch haſte, that he would have been there timely the next day, had he not been unfortunately ſtaid by the way by Robbers, who pretending them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Souldiers of the Garriſon of <hi>Ypres,</hi> got together to the number of ſeven, and robbed Travellers with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any regard to their Paſs-ports. They led away the Marqueſs into a very thick Wood, where deceiv'd by his Habit and Paſs-ports, they took him for a Trades-man, and forc'd him to draw a Bill of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change upon ſome of his Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondents, threatning to kill him if it were not paid at ſight; and that in the mean time he ſhould ſtay with them for ſecurity. The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs was in no ſmall perplexity,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:180651:33"/>not knowing who to draw the Bill on; and if he diſcover'd himſelf, they would certainly kill him, for fear of being puniſht by him when once at liberty: what courſe ſoever he took, death ſeem'd inevitable; but to gain time, he gave them a Bill upon an Inn-keeper at <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> who had been his Servant, and knew his Character. When he had written it in the moſt preſſing terms for payment at ſight, they could not agree which of them ſhould be truſted with it for recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſo conſiderable a Sum: At laſt they pitch'd upon two of their Company whom they put moſt confidence in: The Marqueſs in the mean time endeavour'd to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuate himſelf with the Robbers, letting them know he could ſcarce find in his heart to be angry with them, not doubting but that they had been reduc'd to that way of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving through the avarice of their
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:180651:33"/>Officers, who perhaps defrauded them of the poor Pay their Prince allow'd them; and that he thought himſelf happy, in falling into their hands who us'd him ſo civilly, and were ſatisfied with a little Money. The deſire he had to ſee <hi>Chriſtina</hi> made the Marqueſs deſcend into Complaiſances for ſaving his life, he had diſdain'd to ſtoop to on any other ſcore: Theſe were ſo agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to their humour, that he was preſently very familiar with them, and they us'd him more kindly than at firſt, and made him ſup with them. The morrow betimes they ſent away one of their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rades to buy in Proviſions; the Marqueſs ſeeing their number leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen'd, and fearing the return of thoſe who were gone to receive the Money on his Bill, reſolv'd to ſeize one of their Swords, and die at leaſt with his Weapon in his hand. One of the four who ſtaid
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:180651:34"/>in the Wood, watch'd always while the other ſlept: The Marqueſs feigning himſelf very ſleepy, the Watchman obſerving it himſelf, went a little further into the Wood. The Marqueſs to loſe no time, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly ſeiz'd their Guns before a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them awak'd: but being too generous to kill men in their ſleep, he took out the priming out of two of the Guns, having the other two in readineſs to be diſcharged: Then went he to meet him who was gone into the Wood, and having threatned to kill him if he made the leaſt reſiſtance, he told him he was unwilling to take the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage he had againſt him, and his Fellows, and was content they ſhould have the Money on the Bill of Exchange, but that for his ſafe paſſage through the Wood he muſt have his company a League fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, aſſuring him he would do him no harm. The Robber believing a
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:180651:34"/>Trades-man incapable of ſo bold a reſolution, and aſtoniſht to hear him ſpeak ſo ſtoutly, was forc'd to obey, and do whatever the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs commanded him. They were ſcarce got out of the Wood, but they were met by a Party of Horſe of the Garriſon of <hi>Lille.</hi> The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs immediately preſented his Paſs-port; but having been taken with two Piſtols about him, and in a quarter very ſuſpitious, they told him, he made uſe of his Paſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports to rob the more ſafely: The Marqueſs to clear himſelf, told them, he had been robb'd in that Wood, and related truly what had paſt, and how he had eſcap'd out of the Robbers hands, which made the Troopers reſolve to enter the Wood to ſeize upon the Thieves. But the Commander having be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thought himſelf this diſcourſe might be a meer invention of the Marqueſſes, to draw them perhaps
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:180651:35"/>into ſome Ambuſh, ordered only ten Horſemen to diſmount, and g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> into the quarter the Priſoner ſhould lead them, where they found th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Rogues, and took them without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance. They were all brought t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Lille,</hi> and having confirm'd all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Marqueſs had ſaid, he had his libe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and no doubt made but he was as he pretended, a Trades-ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> What became of the Robbers, know not, though likely they wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hang'd: But 'tis certain, the Mar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs impatiently longing for new of <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> went ſtrait to the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent where he had been told ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was. When he was come, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> told him there was no ſpeaking with any of the Nuns, that da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> being ſet aſide for receiving <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>French</hi> Gentlewoman into the H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit.</p>
            <p>The reports which had paſt of <hi>Chriſtina</hi>'s having taken that reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, and the Marqueſſes fears,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:180651:35"/>made him believe it was ſhe. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd in this Opinion by his, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate Love, he buſtled through the Croud, and without further inquiry, addreſs'd himſelf to the Prieſt ready to begin the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and pray'd him to ſtay till he had ſpoke with the Abbeſs. Thoſe who obſerv'd with what diſorder he pronounc'd his words, were ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd; and the Prieſt who had prepar'd an Elegant diſcourſe in praiſe of a Religious Life, was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid he ſhould be oblig'd to reſerve it for another occaſion. The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs in the mean time was got to the Grate, and the Abbeſs appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he told her he was come to acquaint her, the Perſon ſhe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to receive into the Number of her Siſters had promis'd him Marriage, and all the Vows ſhe ſhould make would be null. The Abbeſs much ſurpriz'd, call'd the Maid to the Grate, and having told
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:180651:36"/>her what the Marqueſs had ſaid, ſhe charg'd her to declare the truth. The Young Maid, already ſufficiently perplex'd, under the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of that variety of Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions ſhe was to undergo that day, thought the diſcourſe of the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beſs a piece of formality, uſually obſerv'd on ſuch occaſions, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to aſſure her ſelf of the willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of thoſe who took the Habit; and turning toward the Siſter who had the care of her Education, ſhe ask'd her very Innocently, what Anſwer to make. This, and the confuſion in the Marqueſſes coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance at the ſight of a Perſon he knew not, made all believe ſhe was in good earneſt. And the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple cry'd out the man was a Fool. The Marqueſs defended himſelf ſo ill, that the diſtraction of his looks, and his ſilence, made them abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely conclude he was mad; and they drove him out of the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:180651:36"/>without his being able once to make his Complaint.</p>
            <p>While his paſſion procur'd him all this ill uſage, his friends were extremely concern'd for his perſon. The Inn-keeper at <hi>Bruſſels</hi> having been much preſt by the Thieves to pay his Correſpondents Bill of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change, knew the hand, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending he would pay them, went to the Marqueſſes quarters, and ſhew'd the Bill to one of his prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Servants, who confirm'd it was of his Maſters hand-writing, which made them believe he was in the Robbers hands: They ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd themſelves to the Duke <hi>de Montalto,</hi> whom they knew to be his very good friend; and having ſhew'd him the Bill, the Duke cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the two men, who demanded payment of it, to be preſently ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſted; and having ſeverely threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them, they confeſt all. The Duke was in fear for the danger of
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:180651:37"/>his Friend, and went out in Perſon in the Head of a Party of three hundred Horſe, and ſome Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goons. When he came to the Wood where the two Robbers had left their Comrades, he plac'd Guards at all the Avenues, and went in himſelf at the Head of his Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goons, and ſo croſs'd all the Woods, but found not one perſon. This heighten'd his fear, and made him detach three ſeveral Parties, ſending them away into ſeveral quarters, to endeavour a diſcovery where theſe Rogues had their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge, but all to no purpoſe; ſo that he was forc'd to return with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out having any account of his Friend.</p>
            <p>The morrow, a ſervant of the Marqueſſes impatient for news of him, and thinking he might find him at <hi>Lille,</hi> put himſelf into Boors habit, and went in ſearch of him. As ſoon as he was arriv'd at <hi>Lille,</hi>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:180651:37"/>he pretended he had a Letter for <hi>Chriſtina;</hi> and having got her call'd to the grate of the Covent ſhe was in, he ask'd her privately what news of the Marqueſs. <hi>Christina</hi> not able to give him any account of him, the Servant acquainted her with the departure of the Marqueſs from <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> the adventure of the Bill of Exchange, and all other cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of his abſence. <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtina</hi> who found in her heart a ſtronger inclination for the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs than ſhe thought ſhe had, was ſo concern'd for his misfortune, that the trouble ſhe was in at the news convinc'd her of the height of the paſſion ſhe had for him. She earneſtly pray'd the Man to return inſtantly for <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> not to omit any thing, to learn ſome news of his Maſter, and to let her know without delay the ſucceſs of his care. Before ſhe could make an end of theſe few words, her tears be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray'd
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:180651:38"/>the affection of her heart. When the Servant was gone, ſhe paſt ſome hours in thoſe inquie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes none can comprehend but thoſe only who have been in Love. The mean time the Marqueſſes Servant being an honeſt <hi>Fleming,</hi> and very devout, deſpairing to find his Maſter, goes into a Church, and having heartily pray'd God to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire him where to meet with the Marqueſs, he no ſooner turn'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf about toward the Church-door to go out, but he ſpy'd the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs ſtanding before him; and not able to contain himſelf, cry'd out at the Miracle. The Marqueſs alſo aſtoniſht at ſo unexpected an accident, had much ado to make his Man hold his peace; and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving out he was his Comrade, he told thoſe who came running in at the report of the Miracle, that the Man was a little crack'd, and had often ſuch Fits. They got off by
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:180651:38"/>this Artifice, and went into a houſe where the Marqueſs had lain. His Man gave him an account of what had paſt at <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> and of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order <hi>Chriſtina</hi> was in at the news; the tears ſhe ſhed, and the lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble condition he left her in. The Marqueſs, who after the laſt days work durſt not appear at the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent-gate, was raviſh'd with joy at the news of her being ſo concern'd for his misfortunes; and having got her call'd for by his Man, he ſlipt into the Speaking room, and quickly reviv'd her by his preſence. Never was Converſation more tender than theirs; 'twas not in <hi>Chriſtina</hi>'s power to reproach her Lover with any thing the violence of his paſſion for her could not preſently juſtifie. She promis'd him once for all, never to be any mans but his, and pray'd him not to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe himſelf again to ſo many acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, aſſuring him ſhe had already
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:180651:39"/>written into her Country to deſire the Abbot <hi>Dizeſte,</hi> who had the management of her Affairs, to take a journey into <hi>Flanders</hi> to agree with him about her Marriage. The Marqueſs well ſatisfied with theſe fair hopes, that ſhe might be at eaſe, withdrew ſooner than he would have done, and return'd to <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> where his Friends by their joy to ſee him again, convinc'd him of the trouble they were in by the fears they had been under of having loſt him: To keep them in igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, leſt they ſhould diſcover the myſtery of his abſence, he gave out he had loſt himſelf a Hunting, (a Sport he was known to uſe) and was taken by Robbers, who having detain'd him three days, ſet him a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> liberty. This paſt for current, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo very probable, only the Counteſs of <hi>Benavidez</hi> would not believe it, her Jealouſie having gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven her a true gueſs at the cauſe of
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:180651:39"/>his abſence; it vex'd her to that height, ſhe preſently reſolv'd to leave no ſtone unturn'd to break the Correſpondence between the Marqueſs and <hi>Chriſtina.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>About this time news came to <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Troops were on their march: it was very early in the year, and the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Generals were extremely alarm'd to hear of an Army in the Field in <hi>January,</hi> in a very cold ſeaſon. All the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Officers came to <hi>Bruſſels</hi> to aſſiſt the Governour of the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Netherlands</hi> with their counſel in a conjuncture of this impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. Count <hi>Salazar</hi> being ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iv'd there one of the firſt, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving given the Counteſs of <hi>Bena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videz</hi> a Viſit, ſhe endeavour'd to revive his paſſion for <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching him with his indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and acquainting him the ſame time with the dangers his Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val had expos'd himſelf to for a
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:180651:40"/>ſight of her. <hi>Salazar,</hi> who had been diſcourag'd from ſeeing <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtina</hi> by the difficulties appear'd in the attempt, was ſomewhat a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſham'd; and to cover his coolneſs with a plauſible pretence, and let her ſee he had not been wanting to his Duty, he bethought himſelf of putting a Trick on his Kinſwoman, and perſwading her he was more in <hi>Chriſtina</hi>'s Books than ſhe made account. The Counteſs anſwer'd, She could hardly believe it: He of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd to make it out, and deſir'd on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly time to ſtep to his Quarters to do it. 'Twas not long e're he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd, and brought her a very paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate Letter of the Marqueſſes to <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> being the ſame formerly ſpoken of which <hi>Salazars</hi> men cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly got from the Marqueſſes. <hi>Salazar</hi> having in his hand a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which ſo clearly prov'd what he had ſaid, ſhewed it his Kinſwoman, and told her, ſhe might judge by
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:180651:40"/>the Sacrifice <hi>Chriſtina</hi> had made him, how much he was in her fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour. The Counteſs having read the Letter, was very well pleas'd, and thought it very proper and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual for ſetting the Marqueſs and his Miſtreſs at variance: She ſpoke <hi>Salazar</hi> ſo fair, that ſhe prevail'd with him to leave it in her cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, upon her promiſe to make no ill uſe of it; which ſhe kept ſo ill, that the very next moment ſhe went to one of her friends, a Lady of the Marqueſſes familiar acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and having aggravated the dangers the Marqueſs had expos'd himſelf to for ſeeing <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> and the ill conſequence of his paſſion; it might be excus'd, adds ſhe, did <hi>Chriſtina</hi> but love him; which ſhe is ſo far from, that ſhe cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure him, but ſacrifices his kindeſt and moſt affectionate Letters to <hi>Salazar,</hi> who to my knowledge hath ſeveral of them, though he
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:180651:41"/>hath the diſcretion not to ſhew them. To this ſhe added many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther particulars which convinc'd the Lady, and made her believe ſhe could not do the Marqueſs a better office, than to cure him of his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and diſabuſe him as to his O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of <hi>Chriſtina.</hi> She fell to work on the morrow, and made uſe of all means the Counteſs had fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd her with to perſwade the Lover to think no more of ſo faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs a Miſtreſs. The Marqueſs who could not imagine <hi>Chriſtina</hi> capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of falſhood to him, did not eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly believe what was ſaid of her, and would not for a long time ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the ſuſpitions they endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to infuſe into him of her: But this Lady preſſing him to it continually, he promis'd at length to believe what ſhe ſaid, if ſhe would ſhew him one Letter to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince him of the falſhood of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtina.</hi> The Counteſs of <hi>Benavidez</hi>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:180651:41"/>inform'd of this good ſucceſs, ſent the Letter to her good Friend, who having ſhew'd it the Marqueſs ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely diſturb'd him: He read it over and over, and knew it to be the ſame he had writ to <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> and ſhe had ſent him an Anſwer of. He made no longer doubt but ſhe had betray'd him, and his heart re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching him for having been ſo long fool'd by ſo ingrateful a Wretch, he blindly reſolv'd to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare his reſentment, by writing her a Letter full of Scorn and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, and in the moſt vilifying and bitter terms he could invert; which he did to this purpoſe:</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THe Intereſt I have in your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns ingages me to write to you; to furniſh you the means to make new Sacrifices to my happy Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val: But I adviſe you to make good uſe of this Letter, as the laſt you ſhall receive from me. Force your ſelf
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:180651:42"/>no further to comply with me, yet aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure your ſelf I ſhall not envy the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize of</hi> Salazar, <hi>for I hope you will revenge me of him, and will in a ſhort time make a ſacrifice of him al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to another, who could find in your heart to betray the moſt ſincere and moſt paſſionate of Lovers,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>The Marqueſs</hi> d' Oſſeyra.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The Marqueſs had no ſooner written this Letter, but he gave it him who carried the former, char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging him to be gone immediately, and deliver it <hi>Chriſtina.</hi> Ill news fly apace, and the Letter was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered her within two days after the writing it. <hi>Chriſtina</hi> was ſo little acquainted with the language of it, ſhe could hardly believe what ſhe read: We are naturally inclin'd to be ignorant of what we wiſh ſhould not be, and ſhe would fain have been deceiv'd. But ſeeing the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:180651:42"/>Letter unqueſtionably of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſes hand-writing, and knowing the Bearer to be one he confided in, it offended her ſo highly, ſhe thought it below her to juſtifie her ſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt an Accuſation ſo improbable and unworthy her Noble and Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous Soul: And laying aſide, on the ſudden, the gentleneſs and ſweetneſs of her Nature, ſhe angri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly told the man who waited her Anſwer, ſhe would never take the pains to clear her ſelf to a man who thought her capable of Falſhood: And tearing the Letter in pieces in the preſence of him who deliver'd it, ſhe threatned to have him ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended for a Spy, if he went not away immediately, or ever ſaw her face more.</p>
            <p>As haughty and couragious as ſhe appear'd before the Marqueſſes man, it was not in her power to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-rule the infirmity of her Sex, but ſhe burſt out into tears, and was
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:180651:43"/>tormented with a thouſand diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent thoughts. The deſpair ſhe was in preſs'd her to take a courſe that ſhould remove her for ever far enough from the Marqueſs: yet a ſecret inclination (the cauſe where of ſhe knew not) render'd her reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions uncertain and ineffectual. Sometimes ſhe thought to return home, but preſently diſlik'd it, a having lately received a conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſupply of Money, and deſir'd her Friends Conſent to be married to the Marqueſs, which now could be of no other uſe to her, but to procure her the reproaches of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Province, where people naturally love to talk of their Neighbours. A Religious Life pleas'd her as lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle; and after a thouſand reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, finding none ſo agreeable to her humour as the Military, ſhe took a ſtrong reſolution to ſpend the reſt of her days in Arms.</p>
            <p>While ſhe was taking private or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:180651:43"/>for going to another Town to put her ſelf in fit Equipage for War, the Marqueſs (now his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion was over) began to repent all he had done: And having conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd former paſſages, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to find his Miſtreſs leſs guilty, he bethought himſelf that the man who had one of his Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to carry to <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> never came back again, but took Arms for the <hi>French.</hi> This made him believe he had ſold his Letter to <hi>Salazar,</hi> and deſerted the ſervice of his Prince, for fear of being puniſh'd. The quick return of him he had ſent to <hi>Lille</hi> two days before, who brought him the news of <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi>'s indignation, and the Anſwer ſhe had made him, confirm'd his Opinion of the Innocence of his Miſtreſs. He was upon the point of going to caſt himſelf at her feet; but deſirous to know the manner how this Letter came into
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:180651:44"/>the hands of his Rival, he pray'd the Duke <hi>de Montalto</hi> (who was both their friend, and charged them never to queſtion one another) to go to <hi>Salazar,</hi> and intreat him to tell him upon the word of a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, how he came by that Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; aſſuring the Duke, however it had happen'd, he would not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent it, provided he might know the truth, which for other reaſons he was concern'd to be inform'd of.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Salazar</hi> being preſs'd by the Duke to give a poſitive anſwer, was highly diſpleas'd to find him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf reduc'd to ſuch a ſtrait by the indiſcretion of the Counteſs; and after a weak denial, was at laſt oblig'd to confeſs to his Friend the truth of the buſineſs. The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs having made this diſcovery by the Duke, was ready to die for grief, for having upon ſo light <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſuſpected the fidelity of
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:180651:44"/>his Miſtreſs. This was not all his misfortune; for while he thought of going to ask her pardon, news came to <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> that the Monarch of <hi>France</hi> was at the Gates of the ſtrong Tower of <hi>Valenciennes,</hi> which he beſieg'd in a ſeaſon, when the Heroes of former Ages would have thought it impoſſible to have an Army in the Field: Wherein he ſurpaſs'd the Sun (which he hath taken for his Deviſe) ſince the Froſt and the Snow which hinder the appearance of that Luminary, could not retard for one day the courſe of his Conqueſts.</p>
            <p>The ſurprize the <hi>Spaniards</hi> were under at the news, was incredible. Every man had order to be in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs; and the Marqueſs <hi>d' Oſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeyra,</hi> Maſter of the Artillery, had his hands full: yet he was not ſo taken up with the buſineſs of his Charge, but he thought how to make his peace with his Miſtreſs.
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:180651:45"/>But how preſſing ſoever his paſſion was, his duty was more; and he found himſelf under the neceſſity of being content with writing her a Letter, which probably was very ſubmiſſive and kind: What it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd, I cannot give you a certain account, <hi>Chriſtina</hi> having never received it. This Illuſtrious He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roine, who had laid her deſign for ſerving in the Wars, and promis'd her ſelf never more to entertain any paſſion but for Honour, had left <hi>Lille,</hi> and put her ſelf into Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>page, good or bad; and having joyn'd the Kings Army, near <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenciennes,</hi> in a Troopers Habit, and under her former Name S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin,</hi> he made his Court to the Marſhal of <hi>Luxembourg,</hi> who for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly knew him; and having pray'd to be admitted to ſerve him in the quality of <hi>Ayd de Camp,</hi> the generous Marſhal having inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of kindneſs for thoſe who are
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:180651:45"/>handſom, eſpecially if perſons of Merit, granted his requeſt, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd him that very day to carry Orders into ſeveral Quarters of the Camp. <hi>Valenciennes,</hi> which boaſted it ſelf to have been fatal to the <hi>French,</hi> willing to preſerve the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation it had gain'd in the late Wars, made a vigorous defence. This happy beginning put the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards</hi> in hopes the valour of the Inhabitants, aſſiſted with the rigor of the ſeaſon, would give them time to aſſemble their forces, and expect thoſe of their Confederates for raiſing the Siege. But the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Monarch who beſieged it, taking notice of this vigorous re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, and that they were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided to endure a Formal Siege, caus'd them to be attaqu'd a new way, which may ſerve for an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to the Captains in future Ages. For having made a Detach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from his Army, thoſe brave
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:180651:46"/>Souls animated by the preſence and Orders of a General ſo much Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour to others, made themſelves Maſters of all the Out-works in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen day: Nor can it be ſaid it was by ſurprize, or without reſiſtance, eight hundred men having dy'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſpot, in an obſtinate defence of their ſeveral Poſts. The Kings Muſqueteers being foremoſt of the Aſſailants, entred the Town pell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mell with thoſe that fled into it.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not undertake to write the Great Actions done this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable Expedition; I leave it to the Hiſtorians, whoſe buſineſs it is, and ſhall ſpeak only of what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns my Heroine. This Generous Perſon was always near Mounſieur <hi>de Luxembourg,</hi> who being upon the ſervice of the day, commanded that glorious Detachment. S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin</hi> ſeeing that Worthy Marſhal carry his Orders in Perſon through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, thought the aſſiſtance of an
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:180651:46"/>
               <hi>Ayd de Camp</hi> very uſeleſs in ſo hot a ſervice; and having mingled him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf among the Kings Muſqueteers, he entred the Town with them, and ſhar'd in the glory of ſo hardy an Action. The Grenadiers of the Kings Houſhold, and the Regiment of Guards following the next mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the Garriſon laid down their Arms, and the Squadron of Horſe who were drawn up in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket-place were diſmounted. The Townſmen, who never expected an Aſſault of that nature, were ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maz'd to ſee the <hi>French</hi> in the Town, that moſt of them retir'd into the Churches and Monaſteries to avoid the fury of the Souldier.</p>
            <p>While all was yet in confuſion, ſome greedy Souldiers broke into the firſt Houſes they met with; and S. <hi>Aubin</hi> ſeeing no more Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to be gain'd where there was no more reſiſtance, was marching out of the Town; and having by
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:180651:47"/>the way ſpy'd ſome Souldiers en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring a Houſe, which probably be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long'd to ſome Perſon of Quality, his generoſity inſpir'd him to enter among them, to prevent their pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laging it. He preſently met with a young Maid, very handſom, who all in tears threw her ſelf at his feet, praying him to ſave her Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and reſt ſatisfied with the many Goods he ſhould find in the Houſe, which ſhe wholly yielded up to him with all her heart. S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin</hi>'s heart melting at the diſorder and tears of the poor Maid, he put on a face of Authority, and made the Souldiers, partly by civility, partly by force, to get out of doors; and having lock'd them, promis'd the Maid he would protect her, and ſtay by her as long as ſhould be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to ſave her from the inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of the Souldiers. This diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, which in appearance ſhould have diſſipated her fears, ſerv'd on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:180651:47"/>to heighten them: She could not imagine a man cover'd with bloud, and with dirt ('twas not a ſeaſon for duſt) ſhould have ſo much Humanity, but fancy'd he ſav'd her from others, the better to play a Game for himſelf. Prepoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt with theſe thoughts, ſhe ſtood at a diſtance, and in a lamentable tone pray'd him not to leſſen the Greatneſs of the ſervice he had done her, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y offering her violence to no purpoſe, being reſolved ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to loſe her life, than her Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour: Fear nothing, ſaith S. <hi>Aubin,</hi> were you acquainted with me, and knew me better, you would have better thoughts of me: I ſtay here only to guard you, and will be gone as ſoon as you command me.</p>
            <p>This Maids Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>r was gone that morning to Maſs, and the Town was ſo ſuddenly taken, ſhe had not time to return home e're the buſineſs was done. The Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:180651:48"/>who could not find in his heart to ſee his Houſe rifled, retir'd into the Covent of <hi>Capucines,</hi> in company with ſeveral others who expected like uſage, as very well knowing the Rights Victory gives them who take a Town by Aſſault. But the Serene Monarch of <hi>France,</hi> as full of Clemency as Valour, and willing the ſeaſon of the Siege, the taking of the Town, and the uſe of the Victory ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e equally extraordinary, ſent in Mounſieur <hi>de Louvoy,</hi> who by mentioning the Kings Name, preſently ſtaid the fury of the Souldiers, and within a quarter of an hour caus'd better Orders to be obſerv'd in <hi>Valencien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> taken by Aſſault, than had been obſerv'd by the Enemies at three days end in <hi>Treves,</hi> ſurrender'd by Compoſition. 'Tis eaſie to gueſs what a pleaſant ſurprize it was to the Inhabitants, when creeping out of their lurking-holes, and places
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:180651:48"/>of refuge, inſtead of ſmoaking ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes they expected to ſee, they found houſes very well furniſh'd, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd in the ſame condition they had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eft them; and inſtead of Fire and Sword they were ſo juſtly afraid of, they met with Officers coming <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nto their houſes with Gold and Silver in their hands to pay for what they wanted. S. <hi>Aubin</hi> a while after looking out at a Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, ſaw all things quiet by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defatigable cares of the Miniſter I have nam'd: And having obſerv'd the Shops of that great City begin to open, and that his fair Hoſteſs was now out of fear, he went out to ſeek his General, whom he found with his Majeſty, giving him an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the particulars. The Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents of the Maid S. <hi>Aubin</hi> had ſo generouſly protected being return'd home, raviſh'd to find their Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter there, imbrac'd her with inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſible joy. The firſt tranſperes
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:180651:49"/>of this pleaſant Enterview being over, ſhe made them a faithful Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the Obligations ſhe had to the brave <hi>French-man</hi> who ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour'd her, and declar'd the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of the ſervice he had done her ſo much to the life, and how free the Gentleman appear'd from Self-intereſt, that her Father conceiving it not in his power ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently to acknowledge ſo vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and excellent an action; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to clear himſelf from being lyable to an imputation of ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and ſpent two whole days i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſearching (though in vain) for his Daughters Deliverer in the City and Camp. Having heard the Kings Muſqueteers had firſt entre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the Town, he preſently fanci'd the man he look'd for might be one of them. But having acquainted his Daughter with his thoughts, and told her the Muſqueteers were Red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coats, ſhe preſently undeceiv'd him,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:180651:49"/>by aſſuring him, her Protector was in a Habit of a different co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour. Thoſe who are good-na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur'd, will eaſily gueſs what a tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it was to thoſe grateful per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons not to find him they held themſelves ſo much oblig'd to: They were vext at the heart they could not have ſav'd their Goods without being ingrateful, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to make new ſearch for the man, when S. <hi>Aubin</hi> curious to know who ſhe was he had been ſo happy to ſave from the fury of the Souldiers, entred the Houſe by a Back-door, the very ſame he entred by at firſt.</p>
            <p>He croſs'd a little Yard, and found himſelf juſt in the Room of a young Servant-maid, who not fully recover'd of her frights the day before, was ſo troubled to ſee a Stranger in her Chamber, that ſhe ſet up her throat, and with the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oudneſs of her cryes drew all the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:180651:50"/>Houſe to her. They had certainly taken him for a Robber, had no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his good meen, and his Habit which was very decent, made then think him no ſuch man. The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> look'd on him with aſtoniſhment and knew not how to begin ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to him, till the Daughter of the Houſe came in after the reſt, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> knowing S. <hi>Aubin</hi>'s face, cry'd ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>That ſame was her Guardian Ange<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and ſtood at his Elbow in a tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſport of joy with the ingenuity an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> innocence of a true <hi>Flemiſh</hi> Gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> The Father and Mother as ſenſib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as their Daughter of ſo happy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> rencontre, raviſh'd with joy to fin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> themſelves under thoſe ſtrong obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations to ſo lovely a Gentleman imbrac'd him with that affection and kindneſs may better be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood than expreſt. The Father made him an offer of what part b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> pleas'd of his Goods, owning h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> held them of him, by whoſe boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:180651:50"/>and goodneſs alone they were ſtill his. The Mother, who had not yet ſpoke a word, interrupted her Husband, telling him, that in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Gentleman part of their Goods, they paid him only in part for the ſervice he had done them: But ſince he had preſerved <hi>Mary-Anne</hi> their Daughter, dearer to them than all the treaſures of the World, it was but reaſonable to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence ſo conſiderable a good Office to the full, by intreating him to marry her; adding, ſhe was their only Child, and that they had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my'd her to Wife to one of the beſt Gentlemen in their Country. The Father applauded his Wifes Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals, and <hi>Mary-Anne</hi> gave conſent by her ſilence. S. <hi>Aubin</hi> who was not altogether ſo haſty, anſwer'd their offers with a great deal of Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vility, and gave them thanks for the Honour they would have done for him. The modeſty of his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:180651:51"/>heightned their kindneſs, and made them more eager, and put him to no ſmall trouble to reſiſt their preſſing ſolicitations.</p>
            <p>After long diſcourſe, S. <hi>Aubin</hi> being call'd away by his Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, was going off with promiſe to ſee them again; but his intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Father-in-law looking upon him already as his Son, would not run the hazard of ſeeking him in vain, as he had done, over all the Army, but bore him company to his Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. By the way he gave him ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count what a conſiderable Eſtate he had, and forgot not to acquaint him with the perſonal Merits of his Daughter, and the Quality of her Suitors. S. <hi>Aubin</hi> deſirous to put the thoughts of Marriage out of his head, took occaſion to tell him, it would be great wrong to the Fair <hi>Mary-Anne</hi> to be married to a Stranger, who had nothing to truſt to but his Sword, and muſt needs
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:180651:51"/>make her unhappy, by being forc'd the morrow after his Marriage to follow the Camp, and leave her. The grateful Father was ſo far from being diſcourag'd by theſe Reaſons, that having highly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended S. <hi>Aubin</hi> for his modeſty, he imbrac'd him again, and with wonderful frankneſs told him, he thought himſelf the happieſt man on Earth for having it in his power to contribute to the making the Fortune of a Gentleman of ſo ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Worth. With that they parted, and the Father, when re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd home, gave there an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of his diſcourſe with S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin,</hi> magnifying the good Fortune of his Daughter, now likely to be the Wife of a Gentleman, the handſomeſt, the leaſt huffiſh, and the beſt humour'd of any in <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The mean time the Victorious Monarch having given order for he reparations neceſſary for the
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:180651:52"/>ſafety of the place, decamped a few days after; and S. <hi>Aubin</hi> go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to take leave of thoſe who had ſo much kindneſs for him, the whole Family was extremely ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd to ſee him upon going. To be rid of them, he told them, he was under an indiſpenſable neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to follow the Army the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Campagne, upon pain of loſing the little Honour he had gain'd, and the eſteem of all that knew him; yet to ſatisfie their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities, he promis'd in ſome time to come and refreſh himſelf at their houſe for a moneth. The Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther taking notice he ſaid not a word of Marriage, ask'd him if he intended not to be their Son-in-law. S. <hi>Aubin</hi> having thank'd them for the Honour they would have done him, repeated almoſt the very words he had ſaid to the Father on the like occaſion. But being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſir'd to ſpeak more poſitively, he
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:180651:52"/>anſwer'd in general terms, he had never yet thought of Marriage; that in truth he found himſelf ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry averſe from it, and would adviſe them to loſe no time for ſetling their Daughter. The Parents of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended at the Anſwer, thought he ſlighted their Daughter. S. <hi>Aubin</hi> perceiv'd it, and knowing they were troubled at it, he took his oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to ſpeak of <hi>Mary-Anne</hi> with all imaginable eſteem and reſpect: But ſeeing they were not perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his diſcourſe was ſincere, he was at laſt forc'd, for their ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, to make them a promiſe (which they deſir'd of him) that he would never marry any other Maid but <hi>Mary-Anne.</hi> The Father preſented him with a very fine Horſe, which he was oblig'd to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, to avoid utterly diſguiſting them: And having taken his leave, after a thouſand imbraces, S. <hi>Aubin</hi> got again to the Army.</p>
            <pb n="100" facs="tcp:180651:53"/>
            <p>All <hi>Europe</hi> had their eyes fixt on the march of that victorious Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; ſome believ'd, that after an advantage which appear'd rather the work and fruit of an intire Campagne, than a Conqueſt of fifteen days, the King would have return'd to S. <hi>Germain</hi> to refreſh himſelf after ſo great Fatigues, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially when his Majeſty had News from all parts of the moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> to joyn his Troops with thoſe of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> with deſign to oppoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his Majeſties undertakings. Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that great Monarch not us'd to qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his delicious Palaces, to end <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Campagne by the taking of on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Town, how important ſoever, dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled the ſurprize and aſtoniſhment of the World, by pouring his For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces upon <hi>Cambray,</hi> the ſame which the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth had fortifi'd with ſo much care and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, the laſt Age, to heighter
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:180651:53"/>the Trophies of that Great, that Wiſe and Generous King, though the Emperour, when he fortifi'd it, deſign'd it the Bull-wark of the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> and Cittadel of <hi>France,</hi> as the <hi>Spaniards</hi> in the late times called it.</p>
            <p>While the greateſt part of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope</hi> was differently concern'd for ſo famous a Siege, S. <hi>Aubin</hi> was buſie in the ſervice of his General with extraordinary aſſiduity and care, far beyond the uſual rate of <hi>Ayds de Camp,</hi> which the Marſhal <hi>de Luxembourg</hi> ſo well approv'd of, that he choſe to imploy him before any other. The City of <hi>Cambray</hi> being reduc'd to capitulate, the Governour, before he would retire into the Cittadel, deſir'd ſome fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour (the particulars I know not) in behalf of the Wives of the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Officers. Mounſieur <hi>de Lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>embourg</hi> being upon the ſervice of the day in the Trenches, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:180651:54"/>in that Negotiation, ſent S. <hi>Aubin</hi> to Complement the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies from him. He entred the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for that purpoſe; and having learnt that ſeveral of theſe Women were retir'd into a Monaſtery, he went thither; and ſeeing two or three amongſt them, to whom all the reſt paid extraordinary reſpect, he made up to them to ſpeak to them. He had ſcarce begun, but he perceiv'd he ſpoke to the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs <hi>de Benavidez,</hi> who had fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd her Husband to <hi>Cambray,</hi> where his Regiment was. S. <hi>Aubin,</hi> though ſurpriz'd at the ſight of her, endeavour'd to recover him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and would have made an end of his Complement: But the Counteſs, who preſently knew him, would not give him time, but imbrac'd him with ſuch a tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſport, as ſcandaliz'd the Company; this Lady, who always lov'd S. <hi>Aubin,</hi> having then forgot her
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:180651:54"/>Jealouſie that made her hate <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtina.</hi> They ſpent ſome time in private diſcourſe; and S. <hi>Aubin</hi> having told her what great reaſon he had to complain of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs <hi>de Oſſeyra,</hi> the Counteſs who had ſo great a hand in ſetting them at variance, was glad at the heart to hear the News, and pretending her ſelf much concern'd for her, pray'd her to ſhew her the quarrel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Letter he had injuriouſly ſent her. S. <hi>Aubin</hi> having torn it, could not ſatisfie her deſire, but told her the ſubſtance of it, aſſuring her it had occaſion'd her taking Arms a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh, with a reſolution not to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain any paſſion but for Honour and Renown. The Counteſs would gladly have continued this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, but fearing the Company would take it ill, ſhe put an end to it, telling them, this Gentleman having been Priſoner the laſt year at <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> had done her the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:180651:55"/>to viſit her often. S. <hi>Aubin</hi> having confirm'd what the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs had ſaid, retir'd, having offer'd them all the ſervice in his power to obtain the favour they deſir'd; which he perform'd ſo well, that the Ladies were ſatisfi'd, and gave him thanks by Letter.</p>
            <p>The King deſirous his Subjects of the Province of <hi>Boulonnois</hi> might be eas'd of the continual Incurſions of the Garriſon of S. <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> and by his reducing that place might injoy the redreſs his Majeſty intended <hi>Picardy</hi> by the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of <hi>Cambray,</hi> and the quiet all the reſt of the Provinces of his Realm are bleſt with in the heat of War, his Majeſty ordered a Body of an Army to be formed under the Command of his Worthy Brother for beſieging S. <hi>Omer,</hi> the ſame time he lay before <hi>Cambray.</hi> This Enterprize appear'd ſo great, that Strangers doubted the ſucceſs; and
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:180651:55"/>the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> who very well knew the ſtrength of thoſe places, and how well they were provided of neceſſaries for a long reſiſtance, made no great haſte at firſt to ſend their Succours: But frighten'd by the example of <hi>Valenciennes,</hi> they us'd extraordinary diligence to joyn their Troops to thoſe of the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> in order to raiſing the Siege of S. <hi>Omer.</hi> The King ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving notice of their motions, and foreſeeing their deſign, made a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tachment out of his Army, which he ſent under the Command of Mounſieur <hi>de Luxembourg,</hi> in aid of the Duke of <hi>Orleans</hi> before S. <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>While Mounſieur <hi>de Luxembourg</hi> was conducting his Detachment with his uſual activity and vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance, S. <hi>Aubin,</hi> who follow'd him ſtill, and animated by the happy ſucceſs of the Kings Arms, and the Marſhals Illuſtrious example, forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fi'd
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:180651:56"/>his reſolution of continuing in Arms, had by his diligence ſo far gain'd the eſteem of his General, that he took particular notice of him, and imploy'd him on all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable occaſions. This drew on S. <hi>Aubin</hi> the envy of his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rades, particularly a young Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans, whoſe other good qualities prevail with me to conceal his right Name, and to give him that of <hi>Richmond.</hi> This young Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, jealous of the kind uſage S. <hi>Aubin</hi> received from the General Officers, and looking on him as an Upſtart, and a very raw Souldier, let fall on ſeveral occaſions ſome ſharp language againſt him. S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin,</hi> who was naturally good-hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour'd, and had a very inſinuating way, perceiving his diſguſt, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to gain him by fair means, Courting him every day, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting nothing that might oblige him to anſwer his kindneſs by ſome
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:180651:56"/>evidence of affection. <hi>Richmond</hi> had the ill nature to attribute S. <hi>Aubin</hi>'s Civilities and obliging Carriage to his weakneſs, and fear of quarrelling him. This made him more inſolent, ſo that he pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely affronted him on ſeveral oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, reproaching him often with his Womans Face, and telling him a Martial-ſoul ſeldom lodg'd in ſo delicate a body. S. <hi>Aubin</hi> find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf touch'd in ſo nice a point, could not forbear bluſhing at his reproaches; but willing to decline the noyſe of a quarrel, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour'd to put off all with a Jeſt, which did but incourage <hi>Richmond</hi> to be worſe than before. At laſt S. <hi>Aubin,</hi> urg'd by frequent perſecutions, and ſenſible he could no longer conceal his reſentment, without expoſing himſelf to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual affronts, he took his time to find him alone, and tell him he was a-weary of his Raileries, nor would
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:180651:57"/>endure them any longer, but pray'd him, once for all, to put an end to them; otherwiſe he ſhould be oblig'd to let him ſee, he knew how to revenge himſelf, though unacquainted with the ways of gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving affronts. <hi>Richmond</hi> made ſmall account of this diſcourſe, but fell again to his old way of Jeering. S. <hi>Aubin</hi> met him one day on his march, and taking his Piſtol in his hand, told him, he was now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to keep his word with him. <hi>Richmond</hi> having put himſelf in a poſture of defence, S. <hi>Aubin</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging his Piſtol, wounded him in the arm he held his Piſtol by. <hi>Richmond</hi> being diſabled, S. <hi>Aubin</hi> making uſe of his advantage, laid his other Piſtol to his breaſt, threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to kill him, unleſs he would beg his life. <hi>Richmond</hi> obſtinately refuſing, S. <hi>Aubin</hi> inſiſted on't no further, but told him, his obſtinacy ſhould not make him forget to be
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:180651:57"/>generous. Preſently after they were parted by ſome Horſemen that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertook them. The Marſhal of <hi>Luxembourg</hi> having heard of the Combat, caus'd them both to be ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſted; and having carefully in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd into the cauſe of the quarrel, he heard only in general, that S. <hi>Aubin</hi> was the Aggreſſor. This ſurpriz'd him the more, as having ever known him of a ſweet and peaceable humour; which made him believe, he came not to theſe extremities without great provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: So that he reſolv'd to know the bottom of the buſineſs, and found S. <hi>Aubin</hi> had made uſe of all fair means in his power to win over his Adverſary (but all to no purpoſe) before he had ingag'd him. <hi>Richmond</hi> was blam'd for it, and Mounſieur <hi>de Luxembourg</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing he ſhould ſerve any longer under him, ſent him to <hi>Perron,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretence of having his wound
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:180651:58"/>cur'd, though 'twas very light. The Combat prov'd much to S. <hi>Aubin</hi>'s advantage, the General eſteeming him the better for't; and the other <hi>Ayds de Camp</hi> finding 'twas ill jeſting with him, forbore their Raileries.</p>
            <p>Mounſieur <hi>de Luxembourg</hi> was by this time arriv'd before S. <hi>Omer,</hi> juſt as <hi>Mounſieur</hi> was preparing to quit his Lines to go meet the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, though far more numerous. The ſuccour came ſo ſeaſonably, that both Armies being ingag'd, that of the Confederates was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely defeated: The particulars of the Battel have been already ſo faithfully and fully related, I ſhall not attempt writing what is better done to my hand by another; the very relations made of it by the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, attribute all the advantage and glory of it to the Valiant <hi>Philip de France,</hi> who was every-where preſent; reviving their courage
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:180651:58"/>who began to give ground, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimating the whole Army by his Example and Orders.</p>
            <p>S. <hi>Aubin</hi> having ſtill had a long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deſire to ſee a Battel, was hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily glad of being at this: the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Orders he had from his Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral to carry through the Army, gave him the occaſion to ſatisfie himſelf to the full, and to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent where the Victory was moſt ſmartly diſputed. Happening to be at the defeat of a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Battalion of Foot, out of his natural abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of bloudſhed, he ſav'd the lives of two Officers, under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of carrying them Priſoners to Mounſieur <hi>de Luxembourg:</hi> And having ask'd them ſeveral queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons about the condition of their Army, and what Generals they had, he found the <hi>Spaniards</hi> made a Body apart, under the Command of the Marqueſs <hi>de Oſſeyra.</hi> S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin</hi> was ſo troubled at the Name,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:180651:59"/>he ſtood mute for ſome time. He was thinking at firſt to ſeek him out, and demand ſatisfaction with his Arms in his hand for the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage he conceiv'd he had receiv'd from him; but he had ſcarce fram'd his deſign, but he felt his heart fail him, and more concern'd for the perſon of the Marqueſs than it could be for an Enemy. He did what he could to ſuppreſs and get rid of that unſeaſonable tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but all would not do, his heart ſtill hankerd after news of the Marqueſs, and was ſtrongly bent to ſave his life, if poſſible.</p>
            <p>While S. <hi>Aubin</hi> continued under theſe uncertainties, the Kings Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious Brother taking his advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of the diſorder and conſterna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the Enemies were in, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded Mounſieur <hi>de Luxembourg</hi> to purſue them with ſome Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drons: And with admirable fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight, his Royal Highneſs ſent o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:180651:59"/>Troops to poſſeſs themſelves of the Poſts, by which the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, though routed, might have attempted the relief of S. <hi>Omer.</hi> The Duke of <hi>Luxembourg</hi> the mean time being in purſuit of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and perceiving the Dragoons (who ſhould have follow'd him) lag behind, and buſie themſelves in taking Priſoners, which would but hinder the ſervice of the day, he ſent S. <hi>Aubin</hi> with Orders for them to march, and to kill all their Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners. S. <hi>Aubin</hi> carried theſe Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, but with ſome reluctance; yet knowing it his duty to obey, not diſpute the Orders of his Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, he carried them with his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary diligence; and had no ſooner approach'd the Dragoons, but he diſcern'd the Marqueſs <hi>de Oſſeyra</hi> among the Priſoners, which troubled him beyond expreſſion. The Officer who commanded the Dragoons, ſeeing an <hi>Ayd de Camp</hi>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:180651:60"/>coming towards them a gallop, made no doubt but he brought Orders; and having advanc'd a little way to receive them, S. <hi>Aubin</hi> concealing to his power the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize he was in, without loſs of time, he made uſe of that readineſs of wit incident to thoſe of the Sex, and told the Officer, that the Marſhal <hi>de Luxembourg</hi> demanded a Priſoner, nam'd the Marqueſs <hi>de Oſſeyra:</hi> As for the reſt, they ſhould be put to the Sword, and the Dragoons to march up to the Troops, in purſuit of the Enemy. The Order was preſently obey'd, and the Marqueſs conſign'd into the hands of S. <hi>Aubin,</hi> whom he follow'd ſome paces on foot, not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to comprehend by what good fortune he had eſcap'd the fate of the reſt of the Priſoners. The Counteſs of <hi>Benavidez</hi> had told him <hi>Chriſtina</hi> was in the <hi>French</hi> Army, which made him reſolve,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:180651:60"/>after the loſs of the Battel, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe himſelf where he might be made Priſoner, in hopes by that means to have a ſight of his dear <hi>Heroine.</hi> The thought of this flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd him ſo pleaſantly, that he had not yet caſt his eyes on his Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verer, being overjoy'd with his ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving eſcap'd the danger he fear'd of dying with grief, for want of an opportunity to clear himſelf to his Miſtreſs. This joy was but ſhort; for S. <hi>Aubin</hi> to carry on his deſign to the utmoſt, clapt a Piſtol to the Marqueſſes Breaſt, and bid him prepare for death. This troubled the Marqueſs more now than it would have done on another occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; and not able to Maſter his paſſion on the ſudden, he reproach'd S. <hi>Aubin</hi> with his cruelty, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king him languiſh ſo long, when he had reſolv'd to kill him. But reviving himſelf; I will die (ſays he) contentedly, if you will give
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:180651:61"/>me your word to look out in your Army a Cavalier who goes under the Name of S. <hi>Aubin,</hi> and tell him, the Marqueſs <hi>de Oſſeyra</hi> thought upon him to the laſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his life, and had ſome pleaſure in his death, as having been occaſion'd by the Love he had for him. He fixt his eye the while on him he ſpoke to, and began to remember himſelf, when S. <hi>Aubin</hi> being on this occaſion more <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtina</hi> than S. <hi>Aubin,</hi> and having had much ado to act this part with her Lover, diſmounted, and expreſt by her tears the paſſion of her heart, with greater Eloquence than the beſt Orator on Earth could have done it. The Marqueſs by this time knowing <hi>Chriſtina</hi> was his Deliverer, was ſo deeply affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with this new Obligation, that he ſtood ſeiz'd with a pleaſant amazement at the goodneſs of his Miſtreſs, at a time when ſhe had
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:180651:61"/>ſo great reaſon to be angry with him. Yet as joyful as he was for having found her again in ſo extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary a manner, when he call'd to mind he had given her cauſe of offence, it almoſt diſtracted him; and not able to indure the miſery of that condition, he beg'd her par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, in terms ſo ſubmiſſively paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate, that it was readily granted him, before explication made of the myſtery of the Letter which had caus'd that diſorder.</p>
            <p>They had ſcarce underſtood one another, but they found themſelves hemm'd in by a Body of <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Horſe, which the Duke of <hi>Montal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> had ſent to reſcue his Friend out of the hands of the <hi>French.</hi> The Marqueſs was ſo full of Idea's of Love, and appear'd ſo little con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd for a liberty he was no longer Maſter of, that he was not yet ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of his good fortune; when the Duke of <hi>Montalto,</hi> who had
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:180651:62"/>given him up for dead, or a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner, imbrac'd him with all the marks of joy a true Friend could expreſs on ſuch an occaſion. The Duke ſeeing him out of humour, and muſing, imputed it to the ill ſucceſs of their Enterprize, and thinking to comfort him ſaid, their loſs was not ſo great perhaps as they fear'd it on the ſudden, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd him they had taken a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable number of Priſoners. He obſerv'd, in the mean time, the Marqueſs had his eye fixt on S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin,</hi> which obliged the Duke to adviſe him to ſend away that Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner with the reſt, and not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble himſelf with taking charge of him. I owe my life and my liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſays the Marqueſs, to his Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſity; but theſe are the leaſt of my Obligations to him, and the weakeſt reaſons I have to ſhare for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes with him; and then judge you what reaſon I have to ſee him
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:180651:62"/>well us'd. This diſcourſe awaken'd the curioſity of the Duke, and made him look more earneſtly than before on S. <hi>Aubin,</hi> whom after a ſhort view he knew to be the fair <hi>Chriſtina</hi> he had ſeen at <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> and was no ſtranger to her extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Adventures. He gave his Friend joy of his good fortune, and being well acquainted with the paſſion he had for her, he eaſily i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magin'd they had many things to ſay to one another, and diſcreetly retreated, on pretence of fetching up the Straglers of his Troops.</p>
            <p>Though the day of the loſs of a Battel may be thought a time ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry improper for a General Officer to buſie himſelf with matters of Love, the Marqueſs could not forbear en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into a large diſcourſe, to clear all miſunderſtandings between him and his Miſtreſs. After a thouſand reciprocal aſſurances of loving one another for ever, <hi>Chriſtina</hi> repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:180651:63"/>to him the inconveniences ſhe expos'd her ſelf to, by being diſcover'd by ſeveral Officers, as ſhe had been by the Duke <hi>de Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talto;</hi> and made him ſo ſenſible of the injury it would do them both, and what a trouble it would be to her to be the ſubject of diſcourſe for a whole Army, that the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs perſwaded by ſo convincing reaſons, conſented at laſt ſhe ſhould return to the <hi>French</hi> Camp, having faithfully promis'd him ſhe would preſently retire to <hi>Paris,</hi> quit an imployment ſo unſuitable to her Sex, and put her ſelf into a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent till the end of the Campagne, and that ſhe would then marry him; it being her deſire to delay it ſo long, that ſhe might do it with more decency. The Marqueſs in Perſon guarded her as far as he could, and then ordered a Trumpet to bring her ſafe into the Camp. The General was in pain for S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin</hi>
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:180651:63"/>when he arriv'd, and had ſent into ſeveral Quarters to inquire what was become of him: He told him, he had had the misfortune to be taken Priſoner; and that he was let go upon his Parol. Mounſieur <hi>de Luxembourg</hi> believ'd him, and promis'd to ſend the <hi>Spaniards</hi> a Priſoner in Exchange.</p>
            <p>The morrow after the Battel, Mounſieur to make his Victory compleat, by taking S. <hi>Omer,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd to his Camp before the place, and preſs'd it ſo vigorouſly, that they were glad to Capitulate before he was Maſter of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terſcarp: And S. <hi>Aubin</hi> had the pleaſure to be in imployment about his General, the day the place was ſurrendred, as he had been at the taking of <hi>Valenciennes</hi> and <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bray,</hi> Mounſieur <hi>de Luxembourg</hi> having had the good Fortune to Command the ſervice of the day, when every of thoſe places was ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendred.</p>
            <pb n="122" facs="tcp:180651:64"/>
            <p>Three of the moſt conſiderable places of the <hi>Low-Countries</hi> reduc'd under the Kings Obedience, a great Battel won, wherein the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of two great Potentates were defeated; and all this in the height of Winter, and in leſs than ſix Weeks time, are Prodigies Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity will have ſcarce Faith to believe: Yet hardly any were ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd at the News, though very ſurprizing; all who had heard of the Kings Marching in <hi>February,</hi> having expected Actions altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther extraordinary: And we may truly ſay of him, he hath taught the World not to be amaz'd at his extraordinary performances. His Enemies do him right in that parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular. The Court of <hi>Spain</hi> was in ſome Conſternation at the News, the wiſe Prince, who is Prime Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter there, having heard ſome Grandees ſpeak of it with ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize, and attributing the ſucceſs of
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:180651:64"/>the Kings Arms to his good For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, interrupted their diſcourſe, to tell them, his ſucceſs depended more on his Conduct and Merit, than on his good Fortune.</p>
            <p>When S. <hi>Omer's</hi> was taken, the King put his Troops into Quarters of Refreſhment, until the ordinary ſeaſon for drawing them into the Field: And moſt of the General Officers went to taſte the Pleaſures of <hi>Paris.</hi> The Marſhal of <hi>Luxem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourg</hi> being of the number, S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin</hi> to perform the Promiſe made to the Marqueſs, would not loſe ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable an occaſion of accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying the Marſhal to <hi>Paris.</hi> He found himſelf by the way ingag'd in an Adventure extraordinary, as thoſe he had formerly met with. The Duke of <hi>Luxembourg</hi> and Count <hi>Louvigny</hi> going together for <hi>Paris,</hi> the Baron <hi>d' Angoſſe,</hi> who has a dependance upon the Count, having in their March taken notice
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:180651:65"/>of S. <hi>Aubin</hi>'s Countenance, thought he had ſeen him, but could not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the time, or the place: He took occaſion one day to tell him h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> had ſeen him before. S. <hi>Aubin</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> at it, made <hi>d' Angoſſe</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> inquiſitive. Having rack'd his memory a good while, he be thought himſelf at laſt this <hi>Ayd d' Camp</hi> had the Ayr of a Man he had ſeen at Mounſieur <hi>Strasburg's</hi> at a Ball the year before, whom he had taken for <hi>Madamoiſelle de Meyrac,</hi> the only thing that puzl'd him was, that Man was a <hi>Fleming,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Luxembourg</hi>'s People aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd him, this was a <hi>Frenchman,</hi> and had ſerved among the Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queteers. This put him upon a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond addreſs to S. <hi>Aubin,</hi> to pray him to tell him ſeriouſly, if he was not the ſame Perſon who was in Maids habit when he miſtook him for a Gentlewoman of <hi>Bearn.</hi> S. <hi>Aubin</hi> perplex'd to find him ſo
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:180651:65"/>cloſely and buſily curious, thought it better confeſs he had been diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiz'd in Maids Cloaths, than give him occaſion to diſcover he had been diſguiz'd in Mans Apparel. <hi>D' Angoſſe</hi> having learnt what he ſo much long'd to know, told him, they might have very good ſport when they came to <hi>Paris;</hi> and that if he would but put on Womans Cloaths, he ſhould eaſily paſs for <hi>Madamoiſelle de Meyrac,</hi> by the help he would give him, to put a Trick on his Countrymen, which would be excellent divertiſement. S. <hi>Aubin</hi> promis'd him all he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſir'd; both arriv'd at <hi>Paris</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely well ſatisfied, <hi>D' Angoſſe</hi> tickled with the Conceit of his Projects, and S. <hi>Aubin</hi> glad at heart to get rid of his Importunities.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:180651:66"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:180651:66"/>
            <head>New Books Printed and ſold by <hi>J. Magnes,</hi> and <hi>R. Bent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <head>French Books.</head>
               <item>L' <hi>Heureux Eſclave,</hi> in 3 Tomes. 3 s.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Galand Eſcrock.</hi> 12 d.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Le Princeſs de Monferat.</hi> 2 s. 6 d.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Le Grand Viſiers.</hi> 2 s.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Duble Cocu.</hi> 12 d.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Civilities of</hi> France. 1 s. 6 d.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Le Mercury Galand.</hi> 7 Tomes. 7 s.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Le Memoirs de</hi> Sweed. 3 Tomes. 10 s.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Le Memoirs de Silive Demolier.</hi> 6 Tomes. 6 s.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Rare-Entout,</hi> a Comedy. 1 s.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Le Counteſs de Barcellon.</hi> in the Preſs.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Engliſh Novels.</head>
               <item>ZElinda, <hi>by Mounſieur</hi> Scudery, <hi>Engliſhed by</hi> T. D</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:180651:67"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Happy Slave compleat, Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by a Perſon of Quality.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Diſorders of Love.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Cheating Gallant.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Triumphs of Love over For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Heroine Muſqueteer.</hi> Part 1, 2</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Heroine Muſqueteer.</hi> Part 3. <hi>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Preſs.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Almanzor <hi>and</hi> Almanzaid, <hi>a Nov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in the Preſs.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Some new Plays.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>THe Fond Husband, or the Plo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Siſters.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Plain Dealer.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Rival Queens, or</hi> Alexander <hi>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Great.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Deſtruction of</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Parts.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Fool turn'd Critick, in the Pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mithridates, <hi>King of</hi> Pontus.</item>
               <item>Limberham, <hi>or the Kind Keeper.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:180651:67"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
